<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Parallēla dysparallēla, or, The loyal subjects indignation for his royal sovereign's decollation expressed in an unparallel'd parallel between the professed murtherer of K. Saul and the horrid actual murtherers of King Charles I the substance whereof was delivered in a sermon preached at Allhallows Church in Northhampton on (the day appointed for an anniversary humiliation in reference to that execrable fact) Jan. 30, 1660 / by Simon Ford.</title>
            <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 161 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A39917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F1491</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2735</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09527361</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09527361</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43483</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A39917)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43483)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1331:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Parallēla dysparallēla, or, The loyal subjects indignation for his royal sovereign's decollation expressed in an unparallel'd parallel between the professed murtherer of K. Saul and the horrid actual murtherers of King Charles I the substance whereof was delivered in a sermon preached at Allhallows Church in Northhampton on (the day appointed for an anniversary humiliation in reference to that execrable fact) Jan. 30, 1660 / by Simon Ford.</title>
                  <author>Ford, Simon, 1619?-1699.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 50 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for Samuel Gellibrand,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First two words of title in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Charles --  I, --  King of England, 1600-1649 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Samuel, 2nd, I, 14 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43483:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, OR, The Loyal Subjects Indignation, FOR HIS Royal Sovereign's DECOLLATION;</p>
            <p>Expreſſed in an <hi>Unparallel'd PARALLEL</hi> Between the <hi>Profeſſed murtherer</hi> of K. SAUL, and the <hi>Horrid actual Murtherers</hi> of KING CHARLES I.</p>
            <p>The Subſtance whereof was delivered In a SERMON Preached at <hi>All hallows Church</hi> in NORTHAMPTON, On (the <hi>Day</hi> appointed for an ANNIVERSARY HUMILIATION in reference to that <hi>execrable Fact) Jan.</hi> 30. 1660.</p>
            <p>By SIMON FORD B. D. Miniſter there, and Chaplain to his MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for <hi>Samuel Gellibrand</hi> at the Golden Ball in St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43483:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43483:2"/>
            <head>To the RIGHT HONOURABLE JOHN Earl of <hi>LAUDERDAIL,</hi> Viſcount <hi>Metallan,</hi> Lord <hi>Thirleſton</hi> and <hi>Bolton,</hi> One of the <hi>Gentlemen of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Bed-Chamber,</hi> Principal <hi>Secretary of State</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and One of His <hi>Majeſties</hi> moſt Honourable <hi>Privy Council</hi> in <hi>both Kingdoms</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I had the Happineſs to be firſt known to your</hi> Lordſhip, <hi>during your Late</hi> Tyrannical and tedious <hi>Impriſonment at</hi> Windſor <hi>Caſtle (for which I ſtill acknowledge my ſelf obliged to your</hi> own Condeſcention, <hi>inviting me thereunto) I remember your</hi> Lordſhip <hi>was pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint me, that</hi> ſome Books <hi>of mine formerly publiſhed, had been part of the entertainment of your</hi> private hours, <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the</hi> vacancy <hi>which that barbarous Perſecution gave you from</hi> Publick Buſineſs. <hi>And the remembrance hereof em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldneth me to preſume, that your</hi> Lordſhips Library <hi>will af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> this Little Piece <hi>alſo a place among its</hi> Fellows: <hi>Nor</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43483:3"/> 
               <hi>am I altogether out of hope, that it may have the like favour of approbation at your</hi> Lordſhips <hi>hands, from the experience then given me of the value which your</hi> Lordſhip <hi>then aſſured me you put upon</hi> them: <hi>Eſpecially, when I conſider, that the ſubject matter of it is</hi> Loyalty; <hi>for which your</hi> Lordſhip <hi>then ſuffered ſo deeply under the heavy hands of the</hi> Late bloudy Tyrant and Uſurper: <hi>and for which I have been for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years perſecuted by the</hi> Murderers <hi>of our</hi> Late Sovereign of Glorious Memory, <hi>for endeavouring to obſtruct them in the quiet poſſeſſion of his vacant Seat, by both</hi> refuſing to ſubſcribe, <hi>and alſo bearing publick</hi> Teſtimony <hi>from the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit againſt the</hi> Subſcription <hi>of that</hi> accurſed Engagement, <hi>impoſed by them in order to a poſt-juſtification of that</hi> horrid Fact, <hi>the Extirpation of the</hi> Royal Poſterity, <hi>and the Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlement of</hi> themſelves <hi>in their Rights, by colour of a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and</hi> National Conſent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I aſſure you</hi> (my Lord) <hi>that the</hi> Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cience here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of <hi>(together with that little</hi> Contribution <hi>which (in my low capacity) I have (through Gods Goodneſs) lived to give towards the</hi> Reſtauration <hi>and</hi> Settlement <hi>of his</hi> preſent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, <hi>my moſt</hi> Gracious Soveraign, <hi>and</hi> Royal Maſter, <hi>(whom the Divine Protection long preſerve) is not the leaſt of my</hi> Comforts, <hi>nor (I hope) ſhall be to my</hi> dying Day. <hi>Upon the comfortable experience whereof (as alſo upon the conviction of thoſe Doctrines, which in</hi> this, <hi>and my</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Parallel, <hi>I have publiſhed to the world) I am reſolved as long as I live (through Gods Grace) to ſeek the</hi> Peace <hi>and</hi> Welfare, <hi>and Support (to my capacity) the</hi> Crown <hi>and</hi> Dignity <hi>of my moſt</hi> rightful Soveraign, <hi>and bid a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect defiance to all Perſons and Principles whatſoever, that are</hi> given to change.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now the</hi> Lord <hi>grant that the guilt of the Late</hi> Horrid Murder <hi>upon the</hi> Lords Anointed, <hi>may be ſo wiped off from the Score of</hi> theſe Nations, <hi>that we be never viſited with</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:43483:3"/> 
               <hi>thoſe very evils, or worſe, (for a juſt puniſhment thereof) to prevent which, the Contrivers and Executors of it, took ſo ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular and unlawful a courſe. I mean, that the</hi> violent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefulneſs <hi>of ſome</hi> Spirits <hi>among us, may not re-produce ſuch woful</hi> Tragedies, <hi>as God hath mercifully delivered us from once and again, within a few years laſt paſt, and perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually honour his juſt and rightful Succeſsor, our</hi> preſent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign, <hi>with the moſt Noble and Glorious</hi> Title, <hi>of the</hi> Allayer of our mutual heats and animoſities, <hi>the</hi> Modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>of all our</hi> Differences, <hi>and the</hi> Reconciler <hi>of us each to other (even whether we</hi> will <hi>or</hi> no) <hi>by the Interpoſition of his</hi> Royal Authority. <hi>Let <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> be his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual</hi> Motto, <hi>and the</hi> inviolable Obſervation <hi>of all his Acts of</hi> Pardon <hi>and</hi> Oblivion, <hi>be his</hi> Memorial <hi>and Honourable</hi> Remembrance <hi>to all Generations; and may your</hi> Lordſhips Counſels <hi>be perpetually aſſiſtant to Him (as I doubt not but they will) in all things of</hi> that Tendency; <hi>which will not only preſerve your Name in that Repute which you have hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to maintained amongſt all pious and ſober perſons, but render you a Councellor in whom there</hi> will be ſafety <hi>to the Perſon and Throne of his Sacred Majeſty, and make good the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter, which amongſt other your Honourers, have been given of your</hi> Lordſhips <hi>Wiſdom and Temper, by</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Humble and Affectionate Servant, SIMON FORD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:43483:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43483:4"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> OR, The Loyal Subjects Indignation, FOR HIS Royal Sovereign's Decollation, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2 SAM. 1. 14.</bibl>
               <q>And David ſaid unto him, How waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thine hand to deſtroy the Lords Anointed?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Chapter</hi> contains in it <hi>a relation</hi> of certain paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages <note place="margin">The <hi>Introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> to the Text. An <hi>Amalckites Narrative</hi> of the <hi>death of Saul.</hi>
               </note> concerning the <hi>death of King Saul,</hi> (which whether <hi>true</hi> or <hi>falſe</hi> (ſeeing we muſt take them upon the credit of a <hi>fugitive ſouldier)</hi> can hardly be put out of queſtion; though <hi>we,</hi> (as proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly <hi>David,</hi> to whom it was made, <hi>did)</hi> will at preſent ſuppoſe them <hi>true:)</hi> and the <hi>carriage of David</hi> thereupon. The <hi>whole ſtory</hi> whereof ſeems to be recorded
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43483:5"/> of purpoſe for the <hi>vindication of the holy man,</hi> from the unjuſt im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation of <hi>deſigning</hi> and <hi>conſpiring</hi> to take away his <hi>Sovereigns life,</hi> by the <hi>defenſive Arms</hi> which he had formerly <hi>born</hi> againſt him. And <hi>three particulars</hi> are therein mentioned, as evidences of his innocence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. His <hi>unfeigned grief</hi> for that <hi>lamentable death</hi> which (by the relators ſtory) he underſtood had befallen <hi>him,</hi> v. 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His <hi>indignation againſt,</hi> and <hi>juſtice upon</hi> the perſon who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed he was the <hi>inſtrument</hi> to haſten it, <hi>v.</hi> 13, <hi>to</hi> 17.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His <hi>pious endeavour</hi> to perpetuate the memory of his <hi>deceaſed Sovereign</hi> in a <hi>mournfull Ditty</hi> compoſed by himſelf, and appointed in ſucceeding Ages to be ſung in a ſolemn manner by the <hi>children of Judah.</hi> To which purpoſe, he cauſed it to be recorded in a <hi>book</hi> kept (as it ſeems by <hi>Joſh.</hi> 10. 13.) of purpoſe, to preſerve the <hi>memorials</hi> of eminent men, called the <hi>book of Jaſher,</hi> or the <hi>Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right;</hi> and gave it (in remembrance of the weapons of warre which (it appears by 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31. 3.) were moſt fatall in that bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel wherein <hi>Saul</hi> received his foyl, and firſt wound) the title of <hi>Keſheth,</hi> or <hi>the Bow,</hi> of which you have the particular account from <hi>v.</hi> 17. <hi>to the end.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My <hi>Text</hi> comes under the <hi>ſecond</hi> of theſe mentioned particulars, and is the verſe wherein <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth his <hi>deep reſentment</hi> of the related fact, with a juſt horrour and indignation: <hi>David ſaid to him, How waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thy hand to deſtroy the Lords anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which <hi>words,</hi> becauſe rhey relate to a preceding <hi>Narrative,</hi> made by an <hi>Amalekite</hi> (a mercenary of <hi>Sauls,</hi> as is likely, eſcaped out of that battel before mentioned) concerning the <hi>manner of the Kings death:</hi> We will take a little time before we come to a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular view of them, to examine the conſiderable paſſages in it, and circumſtances relating to it.</p>
            <p>And it is obſervable that the <hi>villain</hi> expreſſeth in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> carriage and relation, a ſtrange mixture of</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Confidence.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Managed with a ſtrange</note>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Caution.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Confidence,</hi> in that he took the boldneſſe to be the <hi>Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1. Confidence.</note> of ſuch a <hi>ſtory</hi> concerning <hi>himſelf,</hi> and that in the <hi>face of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> which an ordinary perſon would have trembled to have been charged withall by <hi>another.</hi> And that which moſt ſets off his <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43483:5"/> is, that the perſon before whom he confeſſeth himſelf guilty of promoting <hi>Sauls</hi> death, was his immediate Succeſſoun<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>David,</hi> who by his death became actually <hi>King.</hi> Had he been never ſo ſlightly read in <hi>politicks,</hi> he might have learned, that <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Kings,</hi> (however, they may look on the news of their <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors death</hi> as acceptable tidings, yet) ſeldom look favourably upon thoſe who have been <hi>Inſtruments</hi> in making the royal Seat void for them; as conſidering that the ſame perſons who have been ſo <hi>kind to them,</hi> upon like inducements, may be eaſily tempted to do the <hi>like courteſie for others,</hi> as occaſion ſerves.</p>
            <p>But (it ſeems) <hi>the Wretch</hi> built his <hi>confidence</hi> upon <hi>three probable</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Upon miſtaken grounds.</note> 
               <hi>conjectures,</hi> in all of which (nevertheleſſe) he was ſorely <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>David,</hi> being by <hi>Gods appointment</hi> and <hi>Samuels unction,</hi> the next in ſucceſſion to <hi>Saul,</hi> might by his <hi>greedineſſe</hi> to graſp the <hi>Scepter,</hi> be tempted to make another judgement of the <hi>fact,</hi> then otherwiſe he would; and account his ſervice <hi>meritorious,</hi> who had holpen him to it ſooner then in the courſe of nature it would have fallen. He made an ill conjecture (it appears) at the temper of <hi>Davids</hi> ſpirit, which was not ſo <hi>ſharp-ſet</hi> upon the <hi>diſh</hi> of Royalty (however <hi>tempting</hi> in it ſelf, and to vulgar <hi>appetites)</hi> but that he could <hi>ſtay</hi> till Gods providence in a regular way <hi>carved it</hi> to him. How much mind ſoever he had to the <hi>golden apple,</hi> which ſets all the world at odds, <hi>Dominion,</hi> yet had he no mind to have the <hi>Tret</hi> on which it grew, <hi>battered,</hi> to make it <hi>fall</hi> before the <hi>time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That however <hi>David</hi> might be too mortified to bite at the bait of <hi>Ambition,</hi> yet ſecret <hi>revenge</hi> might tickle him into a good humour, when he underſtood in what manner <hi>divine vengeance</hi> had overtaken his <hi>deadly enemy,</hi> and <hi>implacable perſecutor.</hi> But <hi>David</hi> had learned, <hi>that a gracious ſoul is frequently the more endangered by being ſecure from dangers.</hi> That, <hi>a ſtate of perſecution well husbanded, is the moſt feracious ſoil for grace to thrive in.</hi> That, be the benefit accrewing by the fall of <hi>ones enemy</hi> never ſo great, yet <hi>to rejoyce at the deſtruction of him that hateth us when evil hath found him,</hi> is not only a <hi>vicious diſpoſition</hi> in <hi>morality,</hi> but a <hi>ſin</hi> of no ordinary ſize in <hi>Divinity,</hi> Job 35. 15. and eſpecially, when the <hi>perſon</hi> ſo ſuffering is the <hi>Lords anointed;</hi> and ſo, the <hi>private advantage</hi> accrewing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to any perſon, is too inconſiderable a compenſation to be laid in ballance againſt a <hi>publique loſſe.</hi> And upon this account his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43483:6"/> 
               <hi>politicks</hi> failed the <hi>Relator</hi> in his <hi>ſecond</hi> preſumption.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That <hi>David</hi> had been in <hi>Arms</hi> againſt <hi>Saul</hi> for divers years, and was at this time in a <hi>poſture of defence</hi> againſt him in a <hi>frontier Town</hi> of an enemies Country. Theſe <hi>conſiderations</hi> gave very great <hi>ſuſpicion</hi> that he deſigned the <hi>death of Saul</hi> himſelf, and ſo was (at leaſt intentionally) a <hi>partner</hi> in <hi>guilt</hi> with him who effected it. But the <hi>Miſcreant</hi> either knew not, or was willing not to know that <hi>Davids Arms</hi> were meerly <hi>defenſive,</hi> not <hi>offenſive;</hi> that, as his <hi>warrant</hi> for wearing them was <hi>extraordinary,</hi> and much different from other ſubjects in like caſes, ſo his <hi>temper</hi> in the uſe of them was <hi>extraordinary</hi> alſo: and <hi>laſtly,</hi> that he had <hi>more then once</hi> given evidence of no leſſe, when both <hi>opportunity,</hi> and <hi>tentation</hi> from his moſt intimate friends, had put it to the utmoſt <hi>trial,</hi> 1 Sam. 24. &amp; 26. And thus was he <hi>miſtaken</hi> in his <hi>third</hi> conjecture, which bottomed his <hi>Confidence.</hi> And poſſibly, he himſelf might have ſome twinges and wrenches of ſuſpicion that he might be ſo; and that, in the midſt of his boldneſſe, makes him to manage his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (in the <hi>ſecond</hi> place) with much</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Caution:</hi> Which appears in ſeveral particulars ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable <note place="margin">2. <hi>Caution</hi> in his <hi>Artifices</hi> &amp; <hi>Pleas</hi> for <hi>juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> or <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenuation</hi> of the <hi>Fact.</hi> 1. He relates only the death of <hi>Saul, Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids enemy.</hi> v. 5.</note> in his <hi>carriage</hi> and <hi>narrative,</hi> whereby he ſeems of purpoſe to deſign the extenuation of this fact which he aſſumed the bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thus to relate. As</p>
            <p n="1">1. That though he brought the tidings of both <hi>Sauls</hi> and <hi>Jona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> death, yet he pretends not to have any ſuch particular know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Jonathans</hi> death, as he had of <hi>Sauls,</hi> though <hi>David</hi> asked him concerning them <hi>both;</hi> leſt <hi>David</hi> ſhould by the circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his own relation, have ſuſpected him guilty of <hi>Jonathans</hi> death alſo, as he confeſſed himſelf of <hi>Sauls.</hi> He knew that friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip which was between <hi>David</hi> and <hi>Jonathan,</hi> would have endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered him to a more <hi>ſevere ſcrutiny,</hi> then he hoped he ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo for <hi>Sauls.</hi> At leaſt, he was not ſo ready to inſiſt on that part of the ſtory, which he knew was the moſt <hi>unwelcome,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore choſe to inſiſt only on that which he hoped would be <hi>better entertained.</hi> He had indeed ſlain <hi>Davids enemy,</hi> and ſo could give the moſt perfect relation of his death: but could ſay little but from the voice of the people, concerning the death of <hi>his friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That though he confeſſeth he had an hand in the <hi>death of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">2. He juſtifieth his Fact. 1. By <hi>Sauls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Saul,</hi> yet he was <hi>requeſted</hi> by himſelf to do it. <hi>He ſaid unto him, ſtand upon me, I pray thee, and ſlay me,</hi> ver. 9. Now, <hi>volenti non fit</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:43483:6"/> 
               <hi>injuria;</hi> and how much leſſe, <hi>roganti?</hi> No man is injured, but againſt his will; and therefore, it cannot (in any reaſon) come under the notion of <hi>Injury,</hi> to ſatisfie anothers <hi>Requeſt,</hi> which hath in it a ſuperlative degree of <hi>Voluntarineſs.</hi> Beſides, he was his <hi>Sovereign,</hi> and ſo his <hi>Requeſts</hi> adopted the Authority of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</hi> And if his <hi>Soveraigns Command</hi> might warrant him to take away the life of <hi>another,</hi> why might it not juſtifie him rather in the caſe of his <hi>own?</hi> ſeeing what is a mans <hi>own,</hi> is more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly and directly in his power to diſpoſe of, than what is <hi>anothers.</hi> Add to this; that it was the <hi>laſt Office</hi> of Love and Service that he was capable of performing towards him; and that ſo <hi>great,</hi> that as he had cauſe to believe, that <hi>Saul himſelf</hi> thanked him for it in his dying thoughts, ſo his very <hi>Ghoſt,</hi> if it were preſent, could not but atteſt, that no man ever merited more highly from <hi>Saul,</hi> than he had done.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That there was <hi>Reaſon</hi> enough why <hi>Saul</hi> ſhould account no <note place="margin">By his dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous condition.</note> leſs of this Service, for no man in his condition, but would have <hi>courted death,</hi> more <hi>amorouſly</hi> than ever he did the <hi>deareſt Object of his Affections: Wounded</hi> he was by his own hand, and as one that <note place="margin">Job 3. 21.</note> 
               <hi>longed for death, he had digged for it</hi> into his own Breaſt, as <hi>for hid Treaſure:</hi> But the <hi>Channel</hi> he had made for <hi>Life</hi> to run out at, was too <hi>narrow</hi> to give it a <hi>speedy Vent,</hi> which he ſo earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And how could his eyes endure to ſee his <hi>Beloved Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign</hi> lie in that miſery, wherein <hi>Life</hi> was his greateſt <hi>Burden,</hi> and not <hi>eaſe</hi> him of it? Beſides, Had there been any grounds to hope, he might recover of the wound he had given himſelf, no Subject he had, ſhould have been more ready to have bound it up, and attempted the Cure, than himſelf. But ſure he was, that long he <hi>could not live,</hi> V. 10. And to have protracted his <hi>Life,</hi> when there was only ſo much remaining in him, as ſerved to aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>the anguiſh of his death,</hi> had been the greateſt Cruelty. So that, his condition conſidered, he could not but highly merit, by diſpatching him quickly. Or if his <hi>Charity</hi> to him in that caſe might in any conſtruction be interpreted <hi>criminal,</hi> yet the guilt could not be ſuch, as to render him the <hi>thouſandth part of a Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derer,</hi> ſeeing he could be no further chargeable with it, than that <hi>pitiful fragment of life</hi> amounted unto which he took away. <note place="margin">By the <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlims purſuit</hi> of him.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That had he not done him the <hi>kindneſs</hi> of releaſing his wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſoul, he had undoubtedly faln into the hands of the <hi>uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43483:7"/> Philiſtines,</hi> which he profeſſed to be his great fear, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31. 4. And ſo had <hi>doubly</hi> died by the <hi>Wounds</hi> and <hi>Sarcaſmes</hi> of his <hi>Heathen Enemies.</hi> For, <hi>the Chariots and Horſemen followed hard after him,</hi> V. 6.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That he brought <hi>no deſign</hi> with him to the <hi>place,</hi> where he <note place="margin">By his <hi>unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated</hi> and <hi>providential coming to the place</hi> where he lay.</note> did that <hi>Unhappy Act.</hi> For he was by meer <hi>Providence,</hi> while he fled for his own life, caſt upon that lamentable Object: <hi>He hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened by chance upon Mount Gilboa,</hi> V. 6. and there he <hi>found Saul leaning upon his Spear:</hi> And this conſideration will clear him from all <hi>prepenſed malice,</hi> which is eſſentially requiſite to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute a <hi>Murderer:</hi> So that in this caſe <hi>killing</hi> was no <hi>Murder,</hi> Beſides, ſuch was his <hi>hast,</hi> that he was in, to eſcape with his <hi>own life,</hi> that he had not the leaſt time to deliberate upon any ſuch courſe as might have ſaved <hi>Sauls,</hi> or to debate with himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Lawfulneſs</hi> or <hi>Unlawfulneſs</hi> of the Fact, being hardly himſelf, through his own <hi>fear,</hi> and the <hi>ſuddenneſs</hi> of the <hi>ſurprize</hi> by ſo unexpected a <hi>Providence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. That whereas it might poſſibly be ſuppoſed, that ſome <hi>co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous</hi> 
               <note place="margin">By his <hi>preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Royal spoyles.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>deſire</hi> of enriching himſelf with the <hi>Royal Spoyles,</hi> tempted him to the Fact; to clear himſelf from any ſuch ſuſpition, he had <hi>brought</hi> with him, and now tendered to his Lawful Succeſſor, the <hi>Crown that was upon his head, and the Bracelet that was upon his Arm,</hi> V. 10. Which he took off after he was dead, to preſerve them from worſe hands.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And laſtly, That it had been, and ſtill was his <hi>unspeakable</hi> 
               <note place="margin">By the <hi>moura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing habit</hi> which he made the Relation in.</note> 
               <hi>grief,</hi> that he was ſo unhappy, as to be any way drawn in to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental in ſo ſad a Buſineſs. That he had already ſpent more <hi>Tears for it,</hi> than he <hi>drew drops of blood in it;</hi> not becauſe he thought himſelf in the leaſt criminal, but becauſe he had been ſo unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, as to do that which looked <hi>like</hi> ſo great a Crime. This, though it be not recorded as the Language of <hi>his Lips,</hi> yet ſo much is recorded, <hi>v.</hi> 2. concerning the <hi>Garb</hi> in which he preſented himſelf to <hi>David,</hi> as may juſtifie a conjecture, that he intended it as no ſmall part of his vindication: He had <hi>rent his cloaths,</hi> to teſtifie the <hi>rending of his heart,</hi> and <hi>covered himſelf with aſhes,</hi> to ſhew how willingly he could have laid himſelf down in the duſt for his dear Maſter, if by dying he could have redeemed his Life. <note place="margin">His entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment from <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pleas</hi> as <hi>plauſible,</hi> as ſo <hi>hainous a Fact</hi> could poſſibly admit of. After which, we may ſuppoſe him <hi>pauſing</hi> a while, and <hi>travelling</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:43483:7"/> 
               <hi>with expectation</hi> of ſome great reward from <hi>David,</hi> before whom he feemed to himſelf to have ſo well acquitted himſelf, that he doubted not, but his <hi>Murder</hi> would advance it ſelf to the reputation of <hi>Merit.</hi> But my Text tels you, how <hi>David</hi> diſappointed his <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations,</hi> took down his confidence, and anſwered all his <hi>plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> by ſetting before him the atrociouſneſs of his Fact, <hi>nakedly,</hi> and <hi>in it ſelf</hi> conſidered in mitigation whereof, no <hi>Circumſtances</hi> ought to be admitted to conſideration: For, be all that thou haſt ſaid, true, (replies <hi>David)</hi> yet art thou not in the leaſt excuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For, <hi>How waſt thou not afraid</hi> (upon whatever Motives, or with whatever intentions) <hi>to ſtretch forth thy hand to deſtroy the Lords Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus have I led you through the <hi>Context</hi> to the <hi>Text,</hi> by <note place="margin">Diviſion of the Text.</note> a Preface ſomwhat <hi>tedious</hi> (I confeſs) but yet very <hi>neceſſary,</hi> to the full <hi>underſtanding</hi> and profitable <hi>improvement</hi> of it, as you ſhall ſee hereafter. Mean while, may it pleaſe you, with me, to obſerve, in this Reply of <hi>Davids,</hi> theſe three Parts conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Quid,</hi> or what he replies; That <hi>it was a fearful ſin for him to ſtretch out his hand to deſtroy the Lords Anointed.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Quis,</hi> or the Perſon that made it; <hi>David</hi> ſaid.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Quomodo,</hi> or the manner of his Reply, which is by way of vehement Interrogation: <hi>How waſt thou not afriad,</hi> &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, The <hi>Quid,</hi> or Subſtance of his Reply, importing the Horridneſs of the ſin of this <hi>Amalekite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which there is a twofold Evidence;</p>
            <p n="1">I. The <hi>Aggravations of the Crime</hi> here condemned, taken from,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The <hi>Perſon that committed,</hi> but ought to have <hi>avoided</hi> it with holy <hi>Fear; Thou,</hi> under a <hi>twofold</hi> Capacity:
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Thou, a Private man.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Thou,</hi> a <hi>Subject,</hi> by preſent relation (at leaſt) to <hi>Saul,</hi> being his <hi>Souldier.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>2. The <hi>Perſon on whom</hi> it was committed, and who ought to have been otherwiſe dealt withal, conſidered in a <hi>double</hi> Capacity.
<list>
                     <item>1. Of his <hi>Civil Quality;</hi> He was <hi>Unctus,</hi> a Perſon who had received <hi>Regal Unction,</hi> and was thereby ſeparated from the <hi>Vulgus,</hi> or common ſort of men, a <hi>King</hi> ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43483:8"/>inaugurated, <hi>The Anointed.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. Of his <hi>Sacred Relation,</hi> and ſo he was <hi>Meſſiah Jehovae,</hi> the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> Gods Deputy and Vicegerent by ſpecial Commiſſion.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Fact it ſelf,</hi> which was,
<list>
                     <item>1. In its <hi>Nature,</hi> bloudy, <hi>he deſtroyed him.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. In its <hi>Principle,</hi> voluntary, <hi>he ſtretched forth his hand to do it,</hi> which imports a purpoſe and reſolution of heart to do it.</item>
                     <item>3. In its <hi>Manner,</hi> it was done <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, without fear; He <hi>was not afraid</hi> to do that Act which he ſhould have trembled at.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>II. The <hi>Invalidity of all</hi> his former <hi>Pleas,</hi> or whatever might be urged in his defence; gathered from the connexion of the Verſe with the preceding Relation; <hi>David</hi> takes no notice of any of his Pleas at all, which imports thus much [although all this, and much more might be truly ſaid in his defence, yet it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs horrid to <hi>David,</hi> nor ought to have been to him.]</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Quis,</hi> or the Perſon replying, <hi>David ſaid;</hi> who comes under a <hi>twofold</hi> Conſideration alſo.</p>
            <list>
               <item>I. According to <hi>what</hi> he truly and indeed <hi>was.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As a <hi>man;</hi> one truly <hi>pious,</hi> and incomparably <hi>tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſcienced, [David</hi> (the Saint) <hi>ſaid]</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. As a <hi>King;</hi> For <hi>Sauls death</hi> actually poſſeſſed him of the <hi>Throne,</hi> though he were not poſſeſſed of the <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: [David</hi> (the King) <hi>ſaid.]</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>II. According to the <hi>miſtaken Idea</hi> or <hi>Notion</hi> under which the <hi>Malefactor</hi> repreſented him to himſelf in the grounds of his forementioned <hi>Confidence;</hi> and ſo he comes under a <hi>threefold</hi> view:
<list>
                     <item>1. As a <hi>Perſon</hi> mortally <hi>perſecuted by Saul;</hi> who never left <hi>hunting him as a partridge upon the Mountaines,</hi> till he had hunted him into a Forreign Countrey, where now he was.</item>
                     <item>2. As a <hi>Perſon</hi> formerly <hi>in Arms againſt him,</hi> and yet ſtanding upon his guard, in <hi>Ziglag,</hi> the place of his preſent <hi>Retreat.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. As the <hi>Perſon</hi> who had <hi>long</hi> (by divine Warrant) <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected the devolution of</hi> Sauls <hi>Crown</hi> upon <hi>himſelf.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:43483:8"/>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Quomodo,</hi> or the manner of his <hi>Reply;</hi> which imports an <hi>unuſual heat and eagerneſs,</hi> a ſtrange <hi>concitation of paſſions.</hi> For it is by way of <hi>vehement Interrogation, aculeated</hi> with abundance of quick <hi>Tartneſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is not barely <hi>Aſſertio docentis,</hi> an affirmation of his <hi>Duty,</hi> for then he needed to have expreſt it only thus; <hi>[Thou oughteſt to have been afraid.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor barely, <hi>Querela dolentis,</hi> an expreſſion of his <hi>grief</hi> for the ſad accident: For then he had not needed to have langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged it otherwiſe than thus; <hi>[Alas! What a fearful thing was it for thee thus to ſtretch forth thy hand,</hi> &amp;c.]</p>
            <p>Nor barely, <hi>Quaeſtio diſcentis,</hi> an enquiry concerning the <hi>temper</hi> (or <hi>distemper</hi> rather) wherein he did it, which might have been ſufficiently expreſſed thus; <hi>[Waſt thou not afraid,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>But it is <hi>Interrogatio exprobrantis,</hi> a ſmart interrogation, <hi>expro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating</hi> to him the audacious impiouſneſs of the Fact. <hi>[How waſt thou not afraid,</hi> &amp;c.] Which expreſſeth <hi>all the reſt,</hi> and <hi>more</hi> too. In a word, it ſpeaks three <hi>Paſſions,</hi> which <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> felt upon the ſad Relation.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Grief;</hi> For ſo do we find that Paſſion venting it ſelf by a <hi>doleful Interrogation,</hi> Lam. 4. 1. &amp; Iſa. 1. 21. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Wonder and Aſtoniſhment;</hi> that a Perſon ſo abject and contemptible, ſhould arrive at the confidence to direct a ſteady blow at the heart of his <hi>Soveraign.</hi> And ſuch <hi>[How's]</hi> do we alſo find in Scripture: See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 14. 12. <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 13. &amp;c.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Horrour</hi> and <hi>Abomination</hi> of the monſtrous impiety, as well as daringneſs of the <hi>Act.</hi> And we are not without Examples of the Expreſſion of this paſſion in a like Form. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. 9. <hi>Heſt.</hi> 8. 6. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And thus, having crumbled my <hi>Text</hi> to pieces, for the fuller <note place="margin">And handled.</note> Explication of it, by the due weighing of <hi>every Word</hi> contained in it, it will be needful to look <hi>them</hi> over <hi>ſeverally.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As they relate to the <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>Narrative</hi> contained in it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they may be <hi>accomodated</hi> by way of <hi>parallel</hi> to the <hi>ſad oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion</hi> of <hi>this daies Solemnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, As they <hi>relate to the Chapter</hi> and its <hi>Narrative,</hi> it <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Firſt view</hi> of the <hi>Text.</hi>
               </note> will be uſeful to conſider the <hi>three Parts</hi> of the <hi>Text</hi> diſtinctly, the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43483:9"/> 
               <hi>firſt,</hi> by way of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> the <hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third</hi> by way of <hi>Inference</hi> or <hi>Application.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt then, The <hi>Quid</hi> or <hi>Doctrine</hi> which is by <hi>David</hi> in the <note place="margin">Part 1. <hi>Quid.</hi> Or the <hi>hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of this Fact</hi> of the <hi>Amalekite</hi> in killing <hi>Saul,</hi> and (under that) of <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing</hi> in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral. <hi>Evidenced;</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Text</hi> in ended, to be amplified to the utmoſt, is, the <hi>horrid wickedneſs</hi> of this <hi>particular</hi> Fact of the <hi>Amalekites killing of King Saul (in Hypotheſi)</hi> and thence <hi>(in Theſi)</hi> or <hi>generally, the hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſneſs of the ſin of murdering Kings,</hi> under whatever diminutive conſiderations it may be preſented.</p>
            <p>Now this Intention, <hi>David</hi> in the <hi>Text</hi> doth amply make good, (as before was intimated.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. By ſo emphatical a <hi>Collection of the Circumſtances of the Crime</hi> confeſſed, which the diſtribution of the Text enumerates.</p>
            <p n="2">2. By the <hi>rejecting of all thoſe Pleas</hi> (as invalid) which either were expreſſed, or might be implied, in the particulars of his <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> before mentioned.</p>
            <p n="1">I. The <hi>aggravating Circumſtances</hi> of the Fact, in the Text, are, <note place="margin">Firſt, By the <hi>aggravating Circumſtances.</hi> Taken From the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon committing the Fact.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Conſiderations</hi> under which the <hi>Murderer</hi> came, <hi>(viz.)</hi> of <hi>a private perſon,</hi> and one who (of a <hi>Forreigner,</hi> an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> whoſe life <hi>Saul</hi> had ſpared, contrary to the expreſs <hi>Command of God,</hi> 1 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m. 15.) was admitted into the condition of a <hi>Subject</hi> and <hi>Souldier</hi> under him; and (if the conjecture of ſome, that this <hi>Amalekite</hi> was <hi>Doegs</hi> Son, be true) had received a peculiar Obligation from him, in the advancement beſtowed upon his <hi>Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But (to omit his Obligations, which indeed render the Fact monſtrouſly ingrateful, could they be proved; but being only received from <hi>Jewiſh-Tradition,</hi> and not aſſerted in the <hi>Text,</hi> I ſhall make no further uſe of them) in that he was (confeſſedly) a <hi>private perſon,</hi> and a <hi>Subject,</hi> it was evidence ſufficient of the horridneſs of the Fact, that <hi>he did it.</hi> For, for a <hi>private man</hi> to execu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e a power of <hi>Life and death,</hi> was an high <hi>preſumption,</hi> and would amount to no leſs than <hi>Murder,</hi> if acted upon the <hi>Meaneſt</hi> and moſt <hi>Criminal Perſon</hi> in the world: But when to the <hi>Private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of the <hi>Condition,</hi> is added <hi>Subjection</hi> alſo, this adds a far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter aggravation. Had the <hi>Amalekite</hi> ſlain his <hi>equal,</hi> he had been a <hi>Murderer;</hi> but the ſlaying his <hi>Superior,</hi> to whom he was lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſubject, rendered him a <hi>Parricide.</hi> They that juſtifie the power of <hi>Subjects</hi> over the Lives of their <hi>Lawful Superiors,</hi> had need find
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43483:9"/> out a <hi>Logick,</hi> that can verifie <hi>Contradictions;</hi> for ſuch muſt that Doctrine neceſſarily maintain, that renders the ſame Perſons <hi>ad invicem,</hi> towards each other, and at once, <hi>Soveraign</hi> and <hi>Subject;</hi> the <hi>Subject</hi> his own <hi>Princes Soveraign,</hi> and the <hi>Soveraign</hi> his own <hi>Subjects Vaſſal.</hi> So that the ſin of <hi>King-killing,</hi> acted by the hands of <hi>Subjects,</hi> upon this bare account, amounts to no leſſe than an <hi>Uſurpation of a Juriſdiction</hi> inconſiſtent with all Principles or right Reaſon, and all Lawes, both of God and man, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders the Perſon that is guilty of it, ſuperlatively criminal, as one who forfeits his <hi>Soul</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Life</hi> to <hi>man,</hi> by the guilt of the higheſt <hi>Premunire</hi> that can be incurred. This is the <hi>first</hi> em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical <hi>aggravation</hi> of the Fact, from the <hi>Perſon committing it.</hi> Let <hi>Saul</hi> deſerve to die never ſo juſtly, yet what Commiſſion had the <hi>Amalekite,</hi> a <hi>private Perſon,</hi> and his <hi>Subject,</hi> to kil him? And ſo <hi>David</hi> tels him:
<q>—<hi>At tu indignus quid faceres tamen?</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[How waſt not [Thou] afraid?]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Fact</hi> is yet rendred more <hi>hainous,</hi> by the <hi>Second Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phatical</hi> 
               <note place="margin">From the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon murdered,</hi> who was,</note> 
               <hi>aggravation</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> taken from the <hi>Perſon</hi> ſlain, <hi>Saul,</hi> under a <hi>double</hi> Conſideration:</p>
            <p>He was</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Unctus.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Unctus Domini.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">I. He was <hi>Unctus,</hi> (in his <hi>Civil</hi> Quality) He was a Perſon <note place="margin">Anointed.</note> ſolemnly ſeparated from other men, an <hi>Anointed King. Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> (or whatever Ceremony of Inveſtiture is, (by the Cuſtoms of Particular Nations) equivalent thereunto) puts a Note of higheſt difference between the Perſons dignified therewith, and others. <hi>Three</hi> high and honourable <hi>Functions</hi> in the Scripture were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by this Ceremony of <hi>Anointing,</hi> and all of them ſenced and priviledged from Injuries by vertue of that <hi>Holy Oyle;</hi> the <hi>Prieſtly, Prophetical</hi> and <hi>Royal</hi> Offices. Not to inſtance in the <hi>two former,</hi> (upon which (whatever theſe confuſed times have ſuggeſted to the contrary) it were eaſie to prove, that God hath written a <hi>Nolitetangere,</hi> a Priviledge from common handling) to be ſure the <hi>Laſt,</hi> (the <hi>Royal)</hi> is ſo highly ſecured by the holy Scriptures, that they exact from <hi>Subjects</hi> ſuch a ſpecial Awe and Reverence towards <hi>Kings,</hi> as not only binds the <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Tongue,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43483:10"/> but the very <hi>Heart</hi> alſo, to the <hi>good behaviour:</hi> Whence in the caſe of this very <hi>Saul,</hi> when he was once anointed <hi>King,</hi> the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt puts the Brand of <hi>Sons of Belial</hi> upon all thoſe who <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiſed</hi> or ſpake contemptuouſly of him, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 10. 27. And <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſtrictly forbids us to <hi>curſe,</hi> or wiſh evil to the <hi>King,</hi> even <hi>in our very thoughts, Eccleſ.</hi> 10. 20. So that this Conſideration was very effectually conducing to the aggravation of the <hi>Amalekites</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> and (in him) of every <hi>King-killers</hi> offence: For the conſequence is <hi>a minori ad majus,</hi> undeniable. If the <hi>leſſer</hi> injury may not be done to <hi>Kings,</hi> the <hi>greater</hi> may not. If our <hi>Tongues,</hi> nay <hi>Thoughts</hi> are not to injure <hi>them,</hi> much leſs our <hi>Hands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. To ſtrengthen this conſideration further, <hi>David</hi> cals him <note place="margin">And the <hi>Lords Annointed.</hi>
               </note> not only <hi>Unctum, [Anointed,]</hi> but <hi>Unctum Domini,</hi> [the <hi>Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed]</hi> Which Title peculiarly relates him to God as his Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent and Lieutenant, and enhanceth the ſin of <hi>King-killing</hi> to the guilt of <hi>High Treaſon againſt God</hi> himſelf. That the Title of <hi>the Lords Anointed,</hi> is attributed to <hi>other Kings</hi> beſides <hi>Saul,</hi> as to all the <hi>Jewiſh Kings,</hi> yea and <hi>Heathen Kings</hi> alſo (inſtance <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> Iſa. 45. 1) argues that the ſame ſecurity belongs to <hi>all other Kings,</hi> as being no leſs related to God, and commiſſioned under him: That <hi>Supreme Authority reſides originally in the Body of the People as the Fountain of all juſt power, and is delegated to Kings from</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Not the <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>them, as their ſervants intruſted by them, and for male-adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on accountable to them,</hi> is a Doctrine that ſavours ſo much of a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit quite alien from the Scriptures, that I ſhall almoſt as ſoon turn <hi>Mahometan,</hi> as believe it. Surely in that the Holy Ghoſt cals them <hi>Gods,</hi> he cannot be thought to aſſign <hi>them</hi> an <hi>humane Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,</hi> without allowing the <hi>Creature</hi> a power (which he every <note place="margin">Pſ. 82. 6.</note> where denies him) of <hi>conferring a Divinity</hi> upon the <hi>work of his hands. Man,</hi> whilſt he attempts to make a <hi>God,</hi> doth no other, than the <hi>Child,</hi> that attempts with a <hi>Bundle of Clouts,</hi> to make a <hi>Babe.</hi> They <hi>that ſay to the works of their hands, ye are gods,</hi> Hoſ. 14. 3. are no other, than <hi>blasphemous Idolaters;</hi> and the gods they make, are <hi>Elilim,</hi> vain Idols, not <hi>Elohim,</hi> true Gods, <hi>Jer.</hi> 16. 20. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 96. 5. Yea, it is a ſtrong Scripture-conſequence againſt the <hi>Divinity</hi> of ſuch <hi>Puppet-gods; [The workman made it, therefore it is not God,</hi> Hoſ. 8. 6.] Of like nature is the Preſumption of thoſe men who undertake to <hi>make</hi> and <hi>unmake Kings,</hi> at their own pleaſure; and that ſo great, that (in reference to this very claim) the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43483:10"/> 
               <hi>Great Antichriſt</hi> is juſtly charged with <hi>lifting himſelf up above all that is called God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2. 4. And to <hi>ſet up Kings without God,</hi> (Kings of humane Conſtitution, contrary to Gods appointed Order of Succeſſion) when it was acted by the Ten Tribes, in the caſe of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> and the ſucceeding <hi>Kings of Iſrael,</hi> is yoak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as a parallel piece of preſumptuous Impiety) in one and the ſame verſe, with <hi>making Idols of Silver and Gold,</hi> Hoſ. 8. 4. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a <hi>God</hi> and a <hi>King</hi> of <hi>mans</hi> making, are both alike, <hi>Idols both;</hi> and they that <hi>make them, are like unto them.</hi> It is <hi>He</hi> alone that <hi>hath it to give,</hi> who confers the leaſt ſpark of Divinity, <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical,</hi> as well as <hi>Natural:</hi> and he that ſaies to a <hi>man</hi> of his own ſetting up, <hi>Thou art Gods Deputy,</hi> firſt, robs the <hi>True God</hi> of that power, and then beſtows it upon a <hi>Counterfeit.</hi> And although the Conſtitutions of ſome Nations, where <hi>Popular Election</hi> diſpoſeth of the <hi>Crown,</hi> may ſeem to invalidate this Doctrine, I muſt tell you, that (beſides that <hi>ab initio non fuit ita,</hi> the Original of all Governments was from <hi>Paternal Juriſdiction,</hi> and next that <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Succeſſion</hi> (both appointed by God) and all Forms varying from thoſe, are too novel to preſcribe againſt an ancienter Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution) even there where <hi>Election</hi> (according to Law and Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom) deſignes the <hi>Perſon, Gods Ordination</hi> confers the <hi>Power,</hi> that he is inveſted withall; for <hi>there is no power but from God,</hi> Rom. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Kings</hi> (even where elected by the <hi>People)</hi> are neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs,</note> 13. 1. In ſuch Nations, the Kings may be <hi>Electi, Plebis,</hi> the Peoples Elect; but when once regularly choſen, they become <hi>Uncti Domini,</hi> the Lords Anointed. And with this diſtinction, (though it may poſſibly be, <hi>orthodox enough</hi> to interpret St. <hi>Peters</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>(Pet.</hi> 2. 13.) of a perſon according to the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Customs</hi> of a Nation <hi>elected,</hi> or acknowledged for <hi>King,</hi> that thereby he becomes (ſo far) <hi>an Ordinance</hi> or <hi>Creature of man:</hi> yet) when this <hi>Creature of man</hi> is ſo far <hi>made,</hi> as mans Votes or Laws or Conſents can make him, he receiveth (over and above this) by a Divine <hi>Dixi,</hi> a word of Authority, to make him the Object of conſcientious Obedience, which the ſame Apoſtle in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timates in the next words, <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, i. e.</hi> as conſidering the relation he hath to <hi>God.</hi> The <hi>Body of Authority</hi> is made by <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but the <hi>Soul</hi> of it is infuſed by <hi>God. Prometheus</hi> may make the <hi>Image of a man</hi> of <hi>Clay,</hi> but it is <hi>Fire from Heaven</hi> that muſt <hi>animate</hi> it, or it is but an <hi>Image</hi> ſtill: So till the <hi>Word of God</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43483:11"/> 
               <hi>come to men,</hi> (as our Saviour phraſeth it, <hi>John</hi> 10. 35.) and ſay <note place="margin">Gods Anointed.</note> 
               <hi>Ye are Gods,</hi> they are but (as <hi>Sampſon</hi> bereft of his Locks) <hi>like other men:</hi> But when once Gods <hi>dixi,</hi> is paſt, then, and then only, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> this <hi>Ordinance of man,</hi> becomes <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Constitution</hi> and <hi>Ordination of God,</hi> Rom. 13. 2.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, that (for the aſcertaining of mens Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in the <hi>Object</hi> of their <hi>Civil Worſhip)</hi> Gods <hi>dixi,</hi> alwaies concurs with the <hi>juſt and lawful Iſſue</hi> of Humane <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Cuſtoms,</hi> ſo that God hath given us this <hi>Infallible Note,</hi> to diſcern who is <hi>Unctus Domini,</hi> his <hi>Vicegerent</hi> and <hi>Deputy,</hi> that he comes to govern according to the <hi>Laws of the Kingdom.</hi> But yet you may not aſcribe the <hi>Authority</hi> he hath, to the <hi>Laws</hi> which aſſert his Right, but to <hi>God,</hi> whoſe Conſtitution enables thoſe Laws to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine in ſo weighty a matter.</p>
            <p>And hence, it will not follow, that the <hi>Peoples conſent</hi> (which <note place="margin">And therefore not ſubject to <hi>their Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> when once admitted.</note> made thoſe Laws, upon the determination of which the divine Conſtitution is neceſſarily attendant) renders the <hi>Perſon inveſted with Authority according to thoſe Laws,</hi> at all, much leſs altogether, dependant upon the People for that <hi>Authority;</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in caſe of <hi>male-adminiſtration,</hi> he may be <hi>unmade</hi> by them who <hi>made</hi> him, more than it will follow, that becauſe (accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſtanding Law of Nature) the <hi>rational Soul</hi> is neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly annexed to the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the <hi>Body,</hi> in the <hi>inſtant of Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> therefore we owe our <hi>Spirits</hi> to our Parents, as well as our <hi>Bodies,</hi> or that (upon that Suppoſition) the <hi>Natural Parent</hi> may diſmiſs the <hi>Soul</hi> of his Child from the <hi>Body</hi> at his pleaſure, which he is ſuppoſed to have by generation conferred upon it. But ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (as in <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Reaſon</hi> the Soul of man, however neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily tied to the order of Nature in generation, is yet <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gods Off-ſpring,</hi> Acts 17. Not the <hi>Parents,</hi> and therefore may not be diſlodged our of the Body without a Writ of Revocation, a <hi>Redite Filii hominum,</hi> from <hi>the Father of Spirits, for no man hath</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 3. Heb. 12. 9.</note> 
               <hi>power over the Spirit, but only God that gave it,</hi> Eccleſ. 8. 8. 12. 7. So in the true and genuine <hi>reaſon</hi> of <hi>State-Government,</hi> (which is to be fetched from the Scriptures, not mens Politicks) <hi>Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> which is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> (whatever neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Connexion, by divine appointment, it have to humane Laws and Cuſtoms) cannot juſtly be ſeparated from <hi>the Perſon,</hi> whom thoſe Laws and Cuſtoms have inveſted with it, without an <hi>Act</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43483:11"/> 
               <hi>of divine reſumption.</hi> He that ſaith to Princes, <hi>Ye are Gods,</hi> makes them (in a Political ſenſe) what he ſaies they are, <hi>Civil Deities,</hi> and ſuch they muſt continue, till by a like <hi>dixi</hi> or word of <hi>Repeal,</hi> he unmake them again. And the reſolution which Conſcience muſt expect, to determine herein alſo, muſt be fetched from the Laws Umpirage in all Nations.</p>
            <p>Now from this <hi>Dixi</hi> of God, this Divine Conſtitution it is, <note place="margin">But Sacred &amp; ſecured by <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Ordination</hi>
               </note> that the <hi>Perſons of Kings</hi> have in all places and ages been account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Sacred.</hi> This <hi>Unction from the Holy One,</hi> (give me leave ſo to call it in alluſion to that of St. <hi>John,</hi> though by him uſed in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſenſe, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 20.) ſecures them from the gripes of rude hands, with a <hi>Nolite tangere.</hi> For ſo (though that Text directly relates to Gods wonderful preſervation of the three Patriarchs, <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> and that under the Notion of Gods <hi>Prophets,</hi> under which Relation God expreſly cautions <hi>Abimelech, Gen.</hi> 20. 7. And that Paſſage, it is more than probable, the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt had in his eye, when he penned it) the Argument which God uſeth, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. 15. for the Priviledge he gave them, that they were <hi>Uncti Domini,</hi> will neceſſarily extend the ſecurity there claimed for them, to all who are partakers of a like Unction: <hi>[Touch not</hi> ſaith he, <hi>mine Anointed]</hi> by that known Logical Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ime, <hi>A quatenus ad de omni valet Argumentum.</hi> A conſideration, which ſo far prevailed with <hi>Holy David,</hi> that his <hi>heart ſmote him,</hi> in the Cave, for only <hi>cutting off the Skirt of King</hi> Sauls <hi>Garment,</hi> as if the <hi>ſavour</hi> of the <hi>Divine Unction</hi> by <hi>deſcending</hi> (as it is ſaid of <hi>Aarons,</hi> Pſal. 133. 2.) <hi>to the Skirts of his Garment,</hi> had communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cared its Tincture ſo far to the Royal Robe, as to mind him by the Sent it left upon his very fingers ends, that he had made too bold with the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> 1 Sam. 24. 5. And therefore, no won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <note place="margin">And that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>abuſing</hi> their <hi>Power</hi> againſt the Laws, and <hi>tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Tyrants.</hi>
               </note> if he charge it ſo home upon this <hi>Amalekite,</hi> who had with a <hi>murderous touch</hi> aſſaulted that Body that wore it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> True, (will the <hi>Anti-monarchiſt</hi> ſay) whilſt Princes keep to the <hi>Rules</hi> by which they are to <hi>govern;</hi> but if they <hi>tranſgreſs</hi> them, do they not thereby <hi>forfeit their Priviledge,</hi> and become as <hi>other men;</hi> yea, far <hi>worſe,</hi> by being <hi>Tyrants:</hi> Is it not lawful to <hi>kill a</hi> 
               <note place="margin">which is,</note> 
               <hi>Tyrant,</hi> that preys upon the Lives and eſtates of his Subjects, like a <hi>wild Beaſt let looſe,</hi> and makes uſe of <hi>Gods Authority</hi> committed to him, to ſecure himſelf in ſuch <hi>intolerable Abuſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To which I anſwer,</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:43483:12"/>1. Was not this very <hi>Saul</hi> as properly a <hi>Tyrant</hi> in this kind, <note place="margin">Proved by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</note> as any recorded in Scripture or Hiſtory? Was he impowered by the Law of God (by which he was to govern, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 14, 15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the end) to <hi>perſecute</hi> an innocent <hi>David,</hi> as he did? or to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt the <hi>murder</hi> of his own Son <hi>Jonathan,</hi> as he did? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 33. Or, was he impowered to <hi>deſtroy</hi> a whole <hi>City of Prieſts,</hi> for the ſuppoſed offence of one <hi>Ahimilech,</hi> as he did? 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22. 18. Was he impowered by that Law to do many other irregular Acts, which <hi>Samuel</hi> reckons up by way of <hi>Propheſie</hi> concerning him, when he made him <hi>King? 1 Sam.</hi> 8. 11, 12. And yet was he ſtill <hi>Unctus Domini,</hi> under the Protection of his <hi>Divine Unction,</hi> and not to be <hi>touched</hi> with a violent hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. There is a <hi>twofold Tyrant, Tyrannus Titulo, &amp; Tyrannns exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citio,</hi> a <hi>Tyrant</hi> for want of a <hi>juſt Title</hi> to govern, and a <hi>Tyrant</hi> by <hi>unjuſt Acts</hi> in his Government, though his <hi>Title</hi> to Government be never ſo <hi>juſt.</hi> He that is <hi>Tyrannus Titulo,</hi> and hath no Title to govern, an <hi>Uſurper,</hi> hath no <hi>nolite tangere,</hi> no divine Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from his Unction, no <hi>touch not mine Anointed,</hi> to ſecure him.</p>
            <p>And (although it be not (in my judgment) a ſafe Principle, which permits every <hi>private Perſon</hi> to deſtroy ſuch a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> (ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hereby <hi>private men</hi> are made competent <hi>Judges of Soveraign Rights,</hi> and the moſt <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> cannot be ſafe, if that be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed) yet) no queſtion, the <hi>Collective Body</hi> of a Nation, headed by an <hi>Uſurper</hi> againſt the general ſenſe of thoſe who have the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary power of interpreting and executing Laws, may (upon their call) riſe up againſt, diſpoſſeſſe, and bring him to condigne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment to make way for the <hi>Lawful Prince</hi> unjuſtly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded.</p>
            <p>But where a <hi>Prince lawfully intituled</hi> to his Government, is yet <hi>Tyrannus exercitio,</hi> abuſeth that Government, to unjuſt and ille<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal Barbarities, (though herein he offend as highly againſt God, as it is not eaſily imaginable, how any one can more, becauſe he defaceth <hi>(the moſt glorious Image of God) himſelf;</hi> and reflects the partnerſhip of his guilt upon God, whom he repreſents, as authorizing him to ſuch enormities, which the power received from him (only) capacitateth him to act: yet) is he ſtill, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Anointing,</hi> a priviledged perſon, not to be violated by <hi>thy</hi> hands, or <hi>mine,</hi> whatever evils we ſuffer under him, and what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43483:12"/> capacity ſoever we may be in, to revenge them. I will evidence this to you by a familiar Inſtance: <hi>Adulterated Coyn,</hi> that bears the <hi>Princes Image,</hi> without the warrant of his <hi>own Mint,</hi> to atteſt it, any man may refuſe to receive in payment, and knock to pieces, or nayl to a Poſt, becauſe it is adulterate. But <hi>good</hi> and <hi>lawful Coyn</hi> ſtamped by <hi>juſt Authority,</hi> how much ſoever it may be battered or defaced, whilſt any Print remains of the <hi>Royal In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> to declare it ſuch, may challenge a free paſſage, and may not be refuſed, or wilfully abuſed. So (whatever becomes of <hi>Tyrants by Title,</hi> who bear Gods ſuperſcription only by adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, and are meer <hi>By-blows</hi> of Supremacy) thoſe that are not ſo, (however <hi>Tyrannous</hi> actions may blemiſh and deface them, yet) becauſe they are the Legitimate Iſſue of a Divine Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and ſo truly <hi>Filii Excelſi,</hi> the <hi>Sons of the moſt High,</hi> having the true ſtamp of his Image upon them, muſt be ſtill owned as ſuch, and reſpected according to their Authority.</p>
            <p n="3">3. But be it ſuppoſed, that (notwithſtanding all that is ſaid) ſuch a <hi>Forfeiture</hi> may be made, as the Objectors pretend; I would fain know, who ſhall be <hi>Judge,</hi> when, and by what Acts this <hi>Forfeit</hi> is incurred: Shall the <hi>Prince</hi> himſelf? I doubt they will think that unreaſonable, becauſe in this caſe he is a <hi>meer Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and ſo will undergo the ſuſpicion of Partiality to himſelf, from a Principle of ſelf-Love.</p>
            <p>Who muſt then? The <hi>Collective body of the Subjects?</hi> And do not the Objectors ſee that the ſame reaſon excludes them? Will not the Principle of Self-Love, and Self-revenge be as apt to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt them, in taking cogniſance of the Injuries they feel? But there is an higher exception againſt them yet; and that is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending <hi>Iſraelites</hi> Queſtion to <hi>Moſes, Who made thee a Judge?</hi> Exod. 2. 14. <hi>By what Law either Divine or humane,</hi> (was the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of our Late martyred Soveraign) <hi>can the Subject be impowered to ſit in Judgment upon his King?</hi> And indeed, as there is no ſuch Law, ſo is it moſt unreaſonable there <hi>ſhould be:</hi> For, grant the <hi>Subjects</hi> ſuch a power, and conſidering the prevalency of <hi>prejudices</hi> againſt Governours, and the frequency of ſucceſſeful attempts of ill-meaning perſons, to ſpread thoſe prejudices, together with the incapacity of the People to know and judge of the true reaſon of State-Actions, <hi>&amp;c.)</hi> and tell me, whether it would ever (in like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood be the felicity of any King (how juſt ſoever) without a
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43483:13"/> miracle, to eſcape being depoſed or murthered, at one time or other by his ſubjects. The Complices and Partners in guilt of <hi>every mal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>factor</hi> whom he hath <hi>put to death,</hi> though never ſo juſtly, would before a Popular Judicatory arraign him for <hi>Murther;</hi> the perſons concerned in <hi>confiſcated Eſtates,</hi> would Indite him for <hi>theft</hi> and <hi>robbery:</hi> the <hi>Fanatick</hi> puniſhed by his Laws, for never ſo hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid <hi>Blaſphemies,</hi> and pretended conſciencious <hi>Conſpiracies,</hi> &amp;c. would proſecute him for a <hi>Perſecutor:</hi> inſomuch that the only way for a King to be ſecure in ſuch a Kingdom, were to <hi>let all justice go at ſixes and ſevens,</hi> and then he would be obnoxious to the diſpleaſure of none but (thoſe, who though by this diſſolution of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they would be the deepeſt Sufferers, yet by their conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Principles are remoteſt from all likelihood of revenging <hi>themſelves</hi> upon their Sovereign) <hi>the truly Godly.</hi> Nay (I will ſpeak a <hi>big word</hi> for <hi>once)</hi> it would be hard for the moſt righteous <hi>Governour of the whole world,</hi> to carry himſelf ſo inoffenſively to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his <hi>Subjects,</hi> but that the <hi>major part</hi> of them, were his actions to be ſcanned by their Judgement, would think it fit to Vote the reins out of his hand for male-adminiſtration.</p>
            <p>And if neither <hi>Prince</hi> nor <hi>ſubjects in general</hi> be fit to determine in this Controverſie, who ſhall then? Will they ſay, the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the People?</hi> If ſo, in <hi>what capacity</hi> ſhall they undertake it? Not of <hi>Inferiors</hi> ſurely, or <hi>Equals;</hi> for <hi>par in parem</hi> (much leſs <hi>inferior in ſuperiorem) non habet imperium.</hi> Of <hi>Superiors?</hi> From <hi>whence</hi> ſhall they derive that <hi>power?</hi> If from <hi>Law,</hi> ſhew that Law? If from <hi>popular election,</hi> then their <hi>power</hi> can be no other then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore was in the <hi>body collective</hi> by whom they are choſen; ſo that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the people be ſuperiour to their Sovereigns (which hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore been diſproved,) they cannot delegate that ſuperiority to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, which they never had themſelves.</p>
            <p>And now there remains only <hi>one ſhift</hi> imaginable for the judging this caſe: and that is recourſe to a <hi>Forreign power,</hi> which indeed is ſo farre from amending the matter, that it makes it farre worſe. For (beſides that <hi>Sovereign Princes are equals in Authority,</hi> (though not in <hi>Dominions</hi> it may be) and ſo the former maxim recurres, <hi>Par in parem non habet imperium,</hi> and that none is likely (becauſe of the <hi>precedent)</hi> to be courted to ſuch an Imployment, (except the <hi>Pope,</hi> who challengeth a Supremacy over Princes as Chriſts uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Vicar, and whoſe claims in this kind have been over and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43483:13"/> over refuted:) how ſhall a <hi>Forreign Prince</hi> be enabled to <hi>excerciſe this Juriſdiction,</hi> but by the <hi>ſucceſs</hi> of a <hi>Warre?</hi> And for ſubjects to call in a <hi>Forreign force</hi> to arbitrate the differences between <hi>them</hi> and their <hi>Sovereign,</hi> what can it amount unto but the higheſt of <hi>traiterous Conſpiracies?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. (and laſtly) Suppoſe the <hi>caſe</hi> were <hi>unquestionable,</hi> and the <hi>forfeiture made</hi> and juſtly ſo <hi>judged,</hi> yet, to whom doth the <hi>ſeizure</hi> upon this forfeited Authority belong? Not to <hi>man</hi> (certainly) for it hath been before proved that all <hi>Authority</hi> is <hi>Gods Ordinance,</hi> a <hi>Flower</hi> of his <hi>Prerogative,</hi> a <hi>Jewel</hi> of his <hi>Crown,</hi> and ſo can fall (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forfeiture) only into his hands who derived it. So that it will clearly follow, that if God himſelf (for the chaſtiſement of a ſinfull people, or for other holy ends of his own) ſhall think fit, <hi>for a while,</hi> not to <hi>enter upon the forfeiture,</hi> it will be high preſumption in any men to <hi>precipitate the judgement of God,</hi> and enter <hi>before his time</hi> (though in his <hi>Name</hi> and <hi>right)</hi> upon his peculiar. Hence the <hi>Saints of God</hi> in former and latter times, have ſuffered under the <hi>bloodieſt Tyrants</hi> with admirable patience, as under <hi>Gods ſcourges,</hi> and referred their caſes to <hi>him who judgeth uprightly:</hi> and even in their <hi>complaints</hi> to him, have expreſſed ſo much <hi>Chriſtian temper</hi> and <hi>moderation,</hi> that they have rather praied for the <hi>conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> and <hi>pardon</hi> of their perſecutors, than wiſhed <hi>vengeance</hi> upon them. And when they have foreſeen the vengeance coming, have not <hi>deſired the wofull day,</hi> Jer. 17. 16. but deprecated it rather: However (to be ſure) they never <hi>put forth their hands to the iniquity of ſelf-reparation,</hi> but patiently <hi>expected the coming of the Lord, Ja.</hi> 5. 6, 7. And upon this ground <hi>David</hi> checks the forwardneſſe of <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> (who offered him the ſervice of <hi>ſmiting Saul dead) Deſtroy him not, for either the Lord ſhall ſmite him</hi> (with a diſeaſe) <hi>or his day</hi> (in the courſe of nature) <hi>ſhall come to die, or he ſhall deſcend into the battel and periſh: but the Lord forbid that I ſhould ſtretch forth my hand againſt the Lords Anointed,</hi> 1 Sam. 26. 8, 9, 10. And yet (which makes this <hi>Anſwer</hi> more conſiderable) the <hi>Crown of Saul</hi> was not only <hi>actually forfeited,</hi> but <hi>adjudged ſo by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and the <hi>reverſion</hi> of it beſtowed upon <hi>David,</hi> 1 Sam. 15. 28. Notwithſtanding all which, you ſee, the holy man will not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to make a <hi>forcible entry,</hi> but waits till God by his <hi>providence</hi> devolves that upon him which he had demiſed by <hi>promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It will be farther <hi>objected,</hi> that this priviledge belonged in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43483:14"/> deed to <hi>Jewiſh Kings,</hi> but it may be doubted, whether the <hi>Goſpel</hi> 
               <note place="margin">This priviledg belongs not to Jewiſh Kings only, but all other Kings. <hi>Sol.</hi>
               </note> (introducing a <hi>ſtate of Liberty,</hi> beyond that which the <hi>Jewes</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed,) the ſame immunity belong to <hi>Princes</hi> ſince the <hi>coming of Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To which I anſwer again,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That <hi>Goſpel liberty</hi> diſſolves not Natural or Civil duties: and thoſe that think it does, make it a <hi>cloak of maliciouſneſſe, 1 Pet.</hi> 2. 13, 16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That the immunity of <hi>Jewiſh Kings</hi> belonged not to them as ſuch, but as <hi>Gods Anointed,</hi> as <hi>deputed Gods</hi> under the <hi>moſt high.</hi> And the <hi>Goſpel</hi> owns the <hi>Supream power,</hi> even in the hands of <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting Heathens</hi> as an <hi>Ordinance of God,</hi> Rom. 13. 2.</p>
            <p n="3">3. And it is evident that the <hi>ancient Chriſtians</hi> thought ſo, who after they had adventured their lives in the field <hi>for perſecuting Emperours, as Souldiers,</hi> laid them down <hi>for their Religion,</hi> in obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to their commands (though unjuſt and barbarous) <hi>as Martyrs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> And thus have I diſpatched the <hi>ſecond conſideration,</hi> (that of the <hi>perſon</hi> ſlain) made uſe of in the <hi>Text</hi> for the <hi>ſecond Aggravation</hi> of the <hi>ſin of King-killing:</hi> that <hi>Saul ſlain</hi> was not only <hi>Unctus,</hi> an anointed King, by his civil <hi>Quality,</hi> but <hi>Unctus Domini,</hi> one who was <hi>Gods Vicegerent,</hi> by ſacred <hi>Relation.</hi> And (by conſequence) am now at liberty to inſiſt a while on the <hi>third Aggravation</hi> taken from the <hi>fact it ſelf,</hi> as the <hi>Text</hi> ſtates it. And that is repreſented notoriouſly foul by <hi>three things.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">From the <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> of the <hi>Fact,</hi> as <hi>Bloody.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. That it was <hi>in its nature</hi> bloody. He <hi>deſtroyed the Lords anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi> It was not a murther <hi>intended</hi> only, nor a murther <hi>barely at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted</hi> without ſucceſſe, but an <hi>actual murther.</hi> And yet, had he <hi>not effected</hi> it, the very <hi>attempt</hi> (conſidering the <hi>quality</hi> of the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon)</hi> had been ſo hainous a crime, that the Laws of Nature and Nations would have puniſhed it with death. But here the guilt is infinitely aggravated by the <hi>execution</hi> of that which had been ſo highly criminal but to <hi>attempt.</hi> For a <hi>King,</hi> (however <hi>attempted</hi> againſt) whiles he is but <hi>in being,</hi> fils the Royal Seat, and Heads the Commonwealth, and animates all Courts of Juſtice by the Authority of his Name: yea, laies ſome reſtraint upon the moſt lawleſſe and diſſolute perſons, on the account of a poſſibility of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to account for their outrages and enormities. But the <hi>actual taking away of a Kings life,</hi> expoſeth the empty Throne to the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43483:14"/> next potent Uſurper, ſilenceth the Laws, annulleth all deputed Powers, by the expiration of their Commiſſions, renders every man (in a ſort) his own Maſter, and ſets up (for the Time) as many Lords of miſrule in a Nation, as there are evil-diſpoſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in it. And although theſe evils are not equally felt in <hi>heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Kingdoms,</hi> as in <hi>others,</hi> (becauſe in ſuch <hi>the King never dies)</hi> yet, they are all equally chargeable upon all Regicides; ſeeing, that they do not all actually enſue, is no thank to <hi>them,</hi> but to the <hi>publique conſtitution</hi> rather; and the Fact in its own nature being every where of like pernicious tendency, and ſuch as (even in the beſt conſtituted Governments) may give advantage of opportunity to the deſigns of thoſe who ſhall deſire to improve the alteration of affairs, to the ſubverſion of the Fundamentals of Government, by which ſucceſſion is ſecured; as we of theſe Nations have lately found by too ſad experience. In which reſpect, the <hi>fact</hi> of <hi>this Amalekite</hi> was the more hainous, as being an <hi>actual deſtroying</hi> of the <hi>Lords anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That it was a <hi>voluntary</hi> or rather <hi>wilfull Act.</hi> For he <hi>ſtretched</hi> 
               <note place="margin">wilfull.</note> 
               <hi>forth his hand,</hi> and that with a purpoſe <hi>to deſtroy</hi> the King. Had the <hi>King</hi> accidentally <hi>ruſhed</hi> upon his <hi>drawn weapon,</hi> or had his <hi>armed hand,</hi> by impreſſion from ſome <hi>external force,</hi> been made the inſtrumental cauſe of taking away the life of the <hi>Lords anointed,</hi> or any other like accident had rendred him the <hi>deſtroyer of the King,</hi> though <hi>beſides his intention;</hi> it had been an <hi>infelicity</hi> to have been bewailed all the daies of his life: But to <hi>reach forth</hi> his armed hand to lend him a <hi>voluntary wound,</hi> with a <hi>purpoſe</hi> to take away his life, was a <hi>crime,</hi> not to be expiated with his life it ſelf. Every <hi>ſin</hi> receives its <hi>degrees of ſinfulneſſe</hi> from the <hi>degrees of voluntarineſſe</hi> appearing in it. And the more hainous the ſin is, the more ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravation doth it admit from the <hi>concurrence of the will</hi> in any ſort, becauſe the greater an <hi>evil</hi> is in it ſelf, the more <hi>perverſion of the will</hi> (whoſe only proper object is <hi>good)</hi> muſt there needs be, to render it capable of <hi>chooſing</hi> it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. (and laſtly) That it was committed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> he <hi>was not afraid</hi> to do it. A <hi>modeſt, timorous</hi> ſinner hath ſo much (at leaſt) of the <note place="margin">Audacio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>appearance of vertue,</hi> as abates ſomething of the <hi>odiouſneſſe of the ſin</hi> he commits. But a very ſtrange <hi>monſter of wickedneſſe</hi> muſt he needs be, who hath arrived at the unhappy pinacle of <hi>ſinning dedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently.</hi> To baffle ſhame, and muzzle fear, and ſtifle conſcience in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43483:15"/> ſinning, implies a kind of <hi>abſolute Sovereignty</hi> and <hi>Dominion in wickedneſſe,</hi> and renders the perſon ſo qualified, a kind of <hi>omnipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſinner,</hi> and (by conſequence) the moſt <hi>remote</hi> from all <hi>poſſibility of repentance.</hi> And ſuch a <hi>Wretch</hi> doth <hi>David</hi> imply that man to be, whom neither <hi>Religion</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> nor <hi>reverence</hi> to <hi>Majeſty</hi> will reſtrain from ſo horrid a crime, as this of <hi>deſtroying the Lords anointed,</hi> let whatever can be pleaded on his behalf: Which brings me to the <hi>ſecond</hi> particular <hi>evidence</hi> which <hi>David</hi> gives to the <hi>Quid</hi> or matter of his <hi>Anſwer,</hi> (the <hi>firſt General part</hi> of my Text) which hath waited a long while for its diſpatch,</p>
            <p>And that is, <hi>[the invalidity</hi> of all that <hi>had been,</hi> or <hi>might be pleaded</hi> 
               <note n="2" place="margin">2. The <hi>ſecond</hi> particular <hi>evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence</hi> in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the <hi>matter</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> reply (or the doctrine of the <hi>hainouſnes</hi> of <hi>King-killing)</hi> The <hi>invalidity</hi> of all <hi>Pleas</hi> made for it.</note> on this <hi>malefactors</hi> behalf,] implied in the <hi>connexion</hi> of this <hi>ſowre</hi> and <hi>ſevere expreſſion,</hi> with the <hi>Amalekites garb</hi> and <hi>Narrative,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore improved for his <hi>vindication.</hi> Notwithſtanding all which <hi>David</hi> pronounceth him guilty of the horrid ſin of <hi>murthering the Lords anointed,</hi> and ſentenceth him accordingly. To clear the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of which <hi>Cenſure</hi> and <hi>Sentence,</hi> (ſeeing it will much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce to the main Hypotheſis <hi>[the ſetting forth the horrid wickedneſſe of King-killing]</hi> and be of much uſe to us in our <hi>application)</hi> we will conſider every one of his <hi>real</hi> or <hi>poſſible Plea's</hi> apart, and <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer</hi> them in their order. His <hi>own plea's</hi> are ſeven (before menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned) to which we will adde <hi>one</hi> made by Interpreters of this Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; and that ſhall be the <hi>firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, (though the <hi>Amalekite</hi> pleads it not, yet) there may be a <note place="margin">The <hi>Amalekites</hi> pleas anſwered <hi>Plea</hi> 1. anſwered, (which is the <hi>plea of Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters</hi> for him.)</note> 
               <hi>Queſtion</hi> made, Whether the Holy Ghoſt in the relation of <hi>Sauls</hi> death, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 31. 4, 5. do not acquit him of having any hand in the Fact, though he (in hope of reward) might take it upon himſelf? For the ſtory tels us, that when <hi>Saul</hi> had deſired his <hi>Armour-bearer</hi> to do him the kindneſſe to diſpatch him, and he had refuſed, <hi>Saul took a ſword and fell upon it:</hi> and that he died of that wound by his own hand, ſeems probable by what is immediatly ſubjoined, that <hi>Sauls Armour-bearer ſeeing that he was dead, fell likewiſe upon his own ſword and died.</hi> From hence (with much likelihood) ſome <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters</hi> confidently <hi>acquit</hi> the <hi>Amalekite</hi> from the <hi>Fact.</hi> Nor ſhall I much contend with them about it, ſeeing I ſhall (upon other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts) clear <hi>Davids</hi> juſtice upon him anon. Though I might tell them that there is no cogent reaſon to demonſtrate a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on between the <hi>relation of the Hiſtory,</hi> and the <hi>Amalekites Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</hi> For what if <hi>Saul fell upon his own ſword,</hi> and the <hi>Amalekite</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43483:15"/> ſayes he found him <hi>leaning upon his Spear?</hi> Both may be true; he might (firſt) <hi>fall on his own Sword,</hi> and (that not diſpatching him) might ſcramble up again, and make a <hi>Second Attempt</hi> with his <hi>Spear,</hi> but could not make way through his <hi>Coat of Mayle,</hi> as the Margin to <hi>v.</hi> 9. renders his words to the <hi>Amalekite.</hi> And what if it be ſubjoyned, after his <hi>falling on his Sword,</hi> that his <hi>Armour-bearer ſaw that he was dead?</hi> Doth it therefore follow, that he <hi>died immediately</hi> of that Wound? The <hi>Armour-bearer</hi> might <hi>conclude him dead,</hi> ſeeing him ſo <hi>wounded</hi> and <hi>faln;</hi> when yet he might ſtruggle longer with death, then he imagined, and <hi>out-live</hi> him that thought him dead, even till the <hi>Amalekite</hi> came, and finding him in that ſad poſture, killed him outright.</p>
            <p>But (however) be it that the <hi>Amalekite did the Fact indeed,</hi> or only <hi>boaſted</hi> (in hope of reward) <hi>that he had done it;</hi> yet received he no wrong from <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Voluntary Confeſſion</hi> (eſpecially, where no Force is uſed to extort it, upon publick arraignment, in the preſence of a Judge) is <hi>Conviction ſufficient,</hi> to juſtifie the condemnation of the perſon confeſſing.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Abundance of <hi>Circumſtances</hi> there were to confirm <hi>David</hi> in the belief of it: As,</p>
            <p n="1">1. That he was an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> and ſo one that upon a <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal quarrel,</hi> might be ſuppoſed to owe <hi>Saul</hi> a Miſchief, who had put the whole Nation of which he was, excepting only himſelf, and ſome few more (it is probable) carried away contrary to Gods Command alive for Slaves, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. And it may be (up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this account, in his Examination) <hi>David</hi> asked him again, <hi>whence he was?</hi> V. 13. (though in his Relation of the Diſcourſe between <hi>Saul</hi> and himſelf, he had let fall no leſs before) that he might judicially confeſs that Circumſtance, ſo neceſſary to his Conviction, upon Deliberation.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Bracelet,</hi> which were known to be <hi>Sauls,</hi> gave evidence, that in all probability, he had the Rifling of <hi>dead Saul,</hi> and probably, might <hi>kill</hi> him, that he might <hi>plunder</hi> him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That whether he <hi>committed the Fact,</hi> or no, yet was he guilty of it, <hi>in intention</hi> (at leaſt) otherwiſe he would not have made ſo formal a ſtory to gain from <hi>David</hi> the reputation of having done it, and related it with a kind of <hi>glorying</hi> in it, as an act of <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> towards <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:43483:16"/>
            <p>Inſomuch, that if he were not really <hi>guilty of the Fact, David</hi> was upon theſe evidences, <hi>guiltleſs of his Blood,</hi> and as he tels him, <hi>V.</hi> 16. that <hi>his Blood lay upon his own head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus hath the <hi>firſt Plea</hi> made by Interpreters on his behalf, no other ſtrength than this, <hi>to give farther evidence to the horrid guilt of King-killing,</hi> even though it be granted. For if that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon juſtly died for it, who had (as the Plea ſuppoſeth) <hi>no other guilt</hi> of the Royal Blood upon him, than that he <hi>eſteemed</hi> the ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of it a <hi>meritorious Service,</hi> and ſhewed his <hi>willingneſs to have done it,</hi> by <hi>boasting that he had done it:</hi> What a dreadful Crime muſt it be, to be guilty of the Fact <hi>indeed?</hi> the very <hi>Intimation</hi> of a <hi>good will</hi> whereunto, rendered this <hi>Amalekite</hi> ſo criminal. <note place="margin">His <hi>own ſeven Pleas</hi> anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note>
               <q>Et paſſa eſt Poenas peccandi ſola voluntas?</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea Anſwered. </seg>2</label> But it may be further ſaid (as was before urged) that <hi>Saul</hi> was a <hi>Tyrant,</hi> a <hi>Perſecutor of David,</hi> and his <hi>deadly Enemy.</hi> And it is hard meaſure that he ſhould die by <hi>Davids Command,</hi> who had by this very Fact ſaved <hi>Davids Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this, the Anſwer (from <hi>Davids</hi> Principles) is eaſie: He was indeed <hi>Davids Enemy,</hi> but he was <hi>Davids Soveraign,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi> Beſides, Had <hi>David</hi> been ſo deſirous to be rid of his Enemy in ſuch a way, he needed not to have left that <hi>work</hi> to be done by an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> ſeeing he had refuſed ſuch a <hi>Service,</hi> when offered by <hi>better Friends.</hi> Laſtly, If he were <hi>Davids Enemy,</hi> he ought the rather to do him <hi>Juſtice</hi> upon his <hi>Murderer,</hi> that he might declare himſelf in the execution of Law the more <hi>impartial;</hi> and learn others, that the <hi>private Injuries received</hi> from our <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>lawful Soveraigns,</hi> ought to make no <hi>Impreſſions</hi> upon our <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to the Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea Anſwered. </seg>3</label> But <hi>Saul himſelf deſired him</hi> to put an end to his miſerable life, (the <hi>Amalekites</hi> Second Plea)</p>
            <p>Grant this too. But was he <hi>Saul,</hi> that is, <hi>himſelf,</hi> when he deſired it; Fear, and Guilt, and Anguiſh, and Loſs of Blood and Spirits, and (it may be, over and above) an <hi>evil Spirit from the Lord</hi> (with which he was wont to be <hi>haunted)</hi> may be ſuppoſed at this time, to <hi>intercept the exerciſe of his Reaſon.</hi> And is it the part of a <hi>Sober man</hi> to kill another at his <hi>Requeſt,</hi> when he is out of <hi>his wits,</hi> and underſtands not what he ſaies? Will no Law allow a <hi>mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:43483:16"/> to diſpoſe of his <hi>Goods</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi> and will it warrant him to diſpoſe of his <hi>Life?</hi> Beſides, Who is there that thinks himſelf obliged to gratifie the deſires, or obey the Commands of a <hi>private Perſon in distemper,</hi> by eaſing him of his Life, whenever he thinks it a burden? How much leſs, when the caſe concerns a <hi>publick Magiſtrate,</hi> whoſe Life and Death are of publick concernment, and the Lives of whole Nations are bound up in his? So that the <hi>beſt obedience,</hi> in ſuch a caſe as this, had been, by Principles of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Reaſon to have endeavoured the <hi>reducing of his Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign to a ſober temper,</hi> and till that could have been effected, to have <hi>taken</hi> from him all <hi>Inſtruments of death, bound</hi> up his <hi>wound,</hi> and <hi>ſaved his Life</hi> (as far as in him lay) though againſt his Will.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea Anſwered. </seg>4</label> And be it (which is his third Plea) <hi>that the caſe ſeemed never ſo desperate; and the wound</hi> he had given himſelf, <hi>never ſo mortal</hi> in appearance, yet ſo long as Life remained, all hopes were not va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed. How many perſons have recovered, whom the beſt Phyſitians and Chyrurgions have given over for <hi>desperate?</hi> He ſhould have <hi>endeavoured</hi> his beſt, and then if <hi>Succeſs</hi> had not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the endeavour, the <hi>endeavour</hi> (which was his duty) would have cleared his <hi>Loyalty,</hi> both before God and man. Beſides, Nature and Reaſon incline every man to a deſire of enjoying his Friends, <hi>as long as poſſibly he can,</hi> though all <hi>Prognoſticks</hi> aſſure him, that enjoyment cannot be <hi>long.</hi> We do not think a <hi>Cordial</hi> caſt away upon a <hi>near Relation,</hi> the utmoſt effect whereof, we are aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, cannot be more, then to <hi>respite death for a few minutes.</hi> To be ſure, <hi>all Nations</hi> that are never ſo little reclaimed from Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſm, would with one mouth <hi>condemn him,</hi> who when a dear friend lies <hi>ſtrugling with the pangs of death</hi> it ſelf, ſhould <hi>knock him on the head,</hi> to put him out of his <hi>Pain.</hi> And therefore, what in a like caſe, had been <hi>unlawful</hi> for the <hi>Amalekite</hi> to have done to a <hi>private Relation,</hi> was <hi>notoriouſly criminal</hi> towards the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea Anſwered. </seg>5</label> If it were (as he farther alleadged) really true, that <hi>the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines were in never ſo hot a Purſuit of the flying King,</hi> yet had this <hi>Amalekite</hi> no warrant to <hi>kill him for prevention:</hi> For, might not <hi>Providence</hi> have led them <hi>another way,</hi> and ſuffered none of them to light upon that place where he lay? The <hi>Divine Protections</hi> of Soveraign Princes are many times of kin to Miracle. <hi>Great deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verances giveth he to his Kings, and ſheweth mercy to his Anointed,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:43483:17"/> Pſal. 18. 50. Again, admit, he were never ſo much in danger of falling into the hands of his purſuing enemies, yet who knowes, but he might have lighted into the hand of ſome <hi>Noble Perſonage,</hi> that (in honour) would have ſpared the <hi>Royal Blood,</hi> and thought it more generous, to take a King <hi>Captive,</hi> then (in cold Blood) to have <hi>murdered him,</hi> when he was not capable of reſiſtance? Or if it had been the Lot of a <hi>Mercenary Souldier</hi> to have lighted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, might he not have endeavoured the <hi>Preſervation</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Noble Priſoner</hi> in hope of a <hi>Ranſom?</hi> Nay, had this <hi>Amalekite</hi> been ſure, that all the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> were ſo barbarous, that <hi>never an one</hi> of them, would have ſaved the <hi>Kings</hi> Life, out of <hi>hatred to his Religion,</hi> as well as <hi>Perſon;</hi> yet (had he conſulted either the <hi>honour</hi> of his <hi>Soveraign dying,</hi> or the <hi>ſafety</hi> of his <hi>Soul</hi> after death) it had been far better for him to have left him to <hi>their</hi> Swords, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to perform his Requeſt with his <hi>own.</hi> For had an <hi>Uncircum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed Philiſtine</hi> for his <hi>Religions</hi> ſake, ſlain him, his death had been his <hi>Infelicity,</hi> but not his <hi>guilt:</hi> Nay, thoſe hands that ſlew him upon that account, had <hi>advanced</hi> him to the <hi>honour of Martyrdom;</hi> whereas, to die <hi>precariouſly,</hi> by the hands of a <hi>Subject,</hi> whom his own <hi>puſillanimous intreaty</hi> had prevailed with, to take away his life, rendred him a <hi>cowardly ſelf-murderer</hi> (by <hi>Proxie)</hi> and loſt him not his <hi>Life</hi> only, but his <hi>Honour,</hi> and ('tis to be feared) his <hi>Soul</hi> together. Beſides, If <hi>this Principle</hi> be but admitted, <hi>[That it is not criminal to take away a Kings Life, provided it be done to prevent the killing of him by other hands,]</hi> How can any Princes life be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure? For may not <hi>any one</hi> of <hi>many Conspirators,</hi> juſtifie himſelf, (by this excuſe) for killing the King, that he did it, <hi>to prevent his Fellows?</hi> And would it not be the greateſt and ſubtilleſt piece of <hi>ambition</hi> that could be, in ſuch a caſe, to be the <hi>firſt</hi> of a traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Crew, that ſhould ſtrike the mortal Blow, ſeeing he of all the Company, would be <hi>ſecured of Indempnity,</hi> upon this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, who could obtain the <hi>precedency</hi> in the horrid Fact? Nay, how eaſie would it be, for <hi>any perſon,</hi> (eſpecially, if his own <hi>Suſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> may be admitted for <hi>evidence)</hi> to conceit a <hi>Plot</hi> againſt the <hi>Kings</hi> Life to be contrived by <hi>others,</hi> and then account himſelf at liberty to <hi>kill him for prevention?</hi> However, Suppoſe there could be a caſe in which ſo dangerous a Principle might be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet (ſurely) it muſt be the <hi>last Refuge,</hi> when a ſufficient Trial hath been made of <hi>all Means</hi> to prevent that danger, which
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43483:17"/> threatens a <hi>Princes</hi> Life, and all prove ineffectual. Had this <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekite</hi> done his beſt to have ſaved him from the <hi>Philiſtines;</hi> had he put his <hi>ſhoulder</hi> under his faln <hi>Soveraign,</hi> to lift him out of the <hi>common Road,</hi> into ſome <hi>by-place,</hi> had he taken ſome courſe to <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe</hi> him, that the <hi>Purſuers,</hi> had they lighted on him, might not have <hi>known</hi> him to be the <hi>King;</hi> or any other way tried his utmoſt to ſecure him, he might with more appearance of Innocence, have done him this kindneſs at the very laſt, to have ſlain him himſelf. Was Mount <hi>Gilboa,</hi> or the Coaſt near it, ſo barren of <hi>Buſhes,</hi> or <hi>Pits,</hi> or <hi>Thickets,</hi> or <hi>Hollow Trees,</hi> or <hi>Cottages,</hi> that might have given a diſtreſſed King ſhelter, till the Purſuit was over; that no <hi>ſhift</hi> could be made, to ſhew a <hi>Subjects Loyalty,</hi> whatever the <hi>Succeſs</hi> had been? <hi>Well fare the hearts of ſuch Subjects,</hi> who in like exigences, would have <hi>tried 1000 homely Artifices,</hi> to have ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their <hi>Liege Soveraign,</hi> rather than have taken this courſe of preventing the <hi>cruelty of purſuing Enemies, by murdering him more charitably with their own Hands:</hi> And if none of them ſhould have proved ſucceſſeful, would <hi>have ſtood by him,</hi> to the utmoſt of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and then have <hi>oppoſed</hi> their <hi>own Breaſts</hi> againſt the <hi>drawn Swords</hi> of bloody Purſuers, though they had been ſure to <hi>die with him;</hi> as conſidering, that the Life of the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> was <hi>worth 10000 of theirs,</hi> and that (next him that dies for <hi>Gods-ſake,</hi> there is none who comes ſo near the honour of <hi>Martyrdom,</hi> as he that dies for <hi>Gods Vice-gerents ſake,</hi> his Lawful <hi>Soveraign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, Had the <hi>Philiſtines</hi> killed him, they were in a <hi>double</hi> ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity more <hi>excuſable</hi> than this <hi>Amalekite:</hi> For they were <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors</hi> in a Battel newly gained, and in the heat of purſuit; (and in <hi>National</hi> Wars, the <hi>Conquered</hi> forfeits his life to the <hi>Conquerors</hi> mercy) Nay, they were <hi>Subjects of another Countrey,</hi> and ſo <hi>Saul</hi> was to them but an <hi>Ordinary Perſon:</hi> But this <hi>Murderer</hi> was not only of the ſame <hi>conquered party</hi> with <hi>Saul,</hi> and ſo had no claim to a power of his life by the <hi>Succeſs of the Day,</hi> but one of his own <hi>Subjects</hi> and <hi>Souldiers,</hi> raiſed for the defence of his Perſon, and ſo was obliged by all means (even with the loſs of his own) to <hi>preſerve</hi> (not <hi>take away,)</hi> the Life of his <hi>Soveraign</hi> and <hi>General,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea anſwered. </seg>6</label> It is probable enough (his <hi>Fifth</hi> Plea) that <hi>he came by the meer conduct of Providence,</hi> to the place of this ſad Tragedy, and in his <hi>own Flight</hi> ſtumbled upon <hi>Saul</hi> unawares, and that the <hi>hast</hi> he was
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43483:18"/> in to ſave his <hi>own Life,</hi> ſomwhat diſordered his <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that he had not a <hi>like</hi> freedom of deliberating what was beſt to be do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, <hi>as at other times.</hi> But yet he was an <hi>Amalekite,</hi> and there might be ſomthing of Enmity againſt <hi>Saul,—Altâ mente repoſtum,</hi> upon the account of a <hi>National Fewd,</hi> and in ſuch a diſpoſition (as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice uſeth to be <hi>quickly up</hi> and <hi>ready,</hi> when Providence offers an opportunity of retaliation) this time (how little ſoever it was) might be <hi>long enough</hi> to excite a deſire of <hi>Revenge,</hi> together with a <hi>Plot</hi> to make it ſeem innocent, by pleading the <hi>ſuddenneſs of the Accident</hi> in its excuſe. Beſides, it may ſeem (by his own relation) that he was not in ſo much <hi>hurry of thoughts</hi> by the ſuddenneſs of the Providence, but that he had <hi>Reaſon</hi> enough left, to <hi>give a direct Anſwer to</hi> Saul's <hi>Queſtion,</hi> V. 7, 8. and to <hi>argue himſelf</hi> into the Commiſſion of that bloudy Fact from the <hi>Conſiderations</hi> which he <hi>pleads,</hi> as moving him unto it; and that he was not in ſo much <hi>haſt,</hi> but that he had time enough (by his own confeſſion) to hold a formal Diſcourſe with <hi>Saul,</hi> (too long (one would think) for a <hi>dying</hi> and a <hi>flying</hi> Perſon to dialogue together) and ſurely, he needed not much <hi>longer time,</hi> than he confeſſed he had, (eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſeeing he had <hi>leiſure</hi> enough to inform himſelf, that the Perſon he diſcourſed with, was his <hi>Soveraign)</hi> to reflect upon his own heart this <hi>Queſtion, [What warrant have I to deſtroy the Lords Anoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d?]</hi> So that whatever his <hi>haſt</hi> was to ſave his <hi>own life,</hi> he <hi>made more haſt than good speed</hi> to take away <hi>Sauls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea Anſwered. </seg>7</label> And though he would ſeem <hi>free from any covetous deſign,</hi> tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to ſuch a Fact, that he might enrich himſelf with the <hi>Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al spoyles;</hi> yet, who knows, but th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t was <hi>firſt in his Intention,</hi> and the ground of his Action, though upon <hi>ſecond thoughts,</hi> (conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inghow difficult it would be for him, a <hi>private Souldier,</hi> to make mony of things ſo commonly known, without being queſtioned, <hi>where he had them?</hi> and that to bring them to the <hi>next Succeſsour,</hi> might yield him more <hi>profit,</hi> than he could have <hi>ſold them for)</hi> he afterwards thought it fitter to preſent them to <hi>David?</hi> However, (be it that he <hi>had no intention to diſpoſe of them any other way,</hi> when he committed the Fact yet) was he not hereby much furthered in his excuſe. For could he think, that an <hi>Intention</hi> honeſtly to diſpoſe of the <hi>Royal Ornaments,</hi> would make a compenſation for the <hi>murder of him that wore them?</hi> Surely, if ſo, he was <hi>much out,</hi> in bringing them to <hi>David,</hi> who had now reaſon to value a <hi>Kings</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43483:18"/> 
               <hi>Life</hi> higher than ſo, by the price he could not but ſet on his <hi>own.</hi> Nay more, he could not indeed have given more <hi>loud evidence</hi> againſt himſelf, than by bringing of thoſe <hi>Regalia,</hi> he had done. For hereby he had cut himſelf off from a capacity of pleading <hi>ignorance</hi> of the <hi>Perſon</hi> whom he ſlew; which (if any) would have moſt ſteaded him; for he could not but know, that the <hi>Crown</hi> he brought, was a <hi>Badge of Soveraignty,</hi> and therefore in killing him, on whoſe Head he confeſſed it was, he confeſſed that he knowingly killed the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Plea Anſwered. </seg>8</label> Laſtly, All the <hi>Expreſſions of ſorrow for the Fact,</hi> with which he uſhered in his <hi>Relation,</hi> might be but <hi>feigned</hi> and <hi>formal:</hi> Or if not ſo, yet what proportion was there between a <hi>baſe Varlets Tears,</hi> and <hi>Royal Blood?</hi> It was well that he mourned for the <hi>Infelicity</hi> of his Fact; but it would have been better, if he had repented of the <hi>wickedneſs</hi> of it. And if (ſeeing how it was like to go with him) he might <hi>plead that alſo;</hi> he muſt know, that <hi>repentance,</hi> though it may avail a <hi>murderer</hi> towards the obtaining of his <hi>pardon from God,</hi> yet it is not a Plea ſufficient to indemnifie in a <hi>Court of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Juſtice. Murderers,</hi> eſpecially, ſuch <hi>Atrocious Murderers,</hi> juſtly die, by Gods Law and mans, though truly <hi>penitent.</hi> The <hi>Tears of Repentance</hi> may do much towards the reparation of a mans <hi>own Innocence,</hi> but can do nothing towards a reparation for <hi>anothers Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, if indeed he <hi>repented</hi> of the fact, he could not but be willing to <hi>prevent</hi> (as far as in him lay) the ſpreading of the <hi>leaven of his example</hi> to infect others with a like guilt: and the effectualleſt courſe to <hi>prevent</hi> ſuch crimes for the <hi>future,</hi> is the exemplary pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of thoſe who have <hi>taught</hi> the world to <hi>commit</hi> them.</p>
            <p>And thus have we diſpatched the <hi>firſt part</hi> of the Text (with its reference to the <hi>hypotheſis</hi> of the <hi>Chapter,</hi> and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> couched in it, <hi>The hainouſneſſe of the ſin of murthering Kings.)</hi> Come we now to the <hi>two</hi> remaining, which (in the <hi>perſon</hi> expreſſing his ſenſe of it, and the <hi>manner how</hi> he expreſſeth it) contain the ſubſtance of thoſe <hi>practical Inferences</hi> which it affords for <hi>Application.</hi> And we will begin with the <hi>ſecond</hi> part.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Quis,</hi> or [the perſon expreſſing his <hi>deep ſenſe</hi> of this <note place="margin">Part 2. <hi>Quis,</hi> or the <hi>Perſon</hi> thus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying, <hi>David.</hi>
               </note> horrid Fact,] <hi>David,</hi> who may herein be exemplary to after-Ages, in the <hi>twofold Conſideration,</hi> wherein the diſtribution of my <hi>Text</hi> repreſented him.</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:43483:19"/>
            <p>I. Conſider him according to <hi>what he was,</hi> in a <hi>twofold</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity. <note place="margin">Conſidered, according to <hi>what he was.</hi> In his <hi>perſonal Capacity,</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As a <hi>man,</hi> (in his <hi>perſonal capacity)</hi> and ſo I told you before he was a <hi>truly pious perſon,</hi> an <hi>eminent Saint,</hi> and for nothing more <hi>eminent,</hi> then for <hi>tenderneſſe of Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he was a <hi>perſon truly pious</hi> and <hi>eminent for Saintſhip,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtratively <note place="margin">An <hi>eminent Saint,</hi>
               </note> evident in the <hi>high characters</hi> the Holy Ghoſt every where beſtows upon him. <hi>Gods ſervant David,</hi> is a Title wherein (by the mutual, and that frequent enterchanging of it in Scripture) both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>he</hi> ſeem to <hi>delight.</hi> And ſuch a <hi>ſervant</hi> God thought him, that he ſeems to <hi>boaſt</hi> of his <hi>findings,</hi> when he had <hi>met</hi> with him, as if the <hi>like</hi> were not to be <hi>found again, [I have found David my ſervant,</hi> Pſal. 89. 20.] So <hi>good</hi> a <hi>ſervant</hi> he was, that (as another high expreſſion carries it) God himſelf could hardly <hi>wiſh</hi> or <hi>deſire</hi> a <hi>better,</hi> (allowing the imperfections incident to humane frailty) for he was <hi>[a man after his own heart,</hi> and one that would ſtick at none of his Commands, but <hi>do <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> all his wils.]</hi> A man <hi>ſo good,</hi> that God <hi>takes meaſure</hi> of the goodneſs or badneſs of all his Succeſſors, by the <hi>proportion</hi> or <hi>diſproportion</hi> they bare to <hi>him:</hi> as being ſo far accounted <hi>good,</hi> as they <hi>walked in the way</hi> and <hi>ſteps of their Father David;</hi> and ſo far <hi>bad,</hi> as they <hi>departed from them;</hi> of which frequent Inſtances might be given, would time permit. Yea, <hi>ſo good,</hi> that the beſt of men that ever was (the Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt)</hi> is by the Holy Ghoſt, called by the Name of <hi>David</hi> as his moſt ſutable <hi>Type,</hi> Jer. 30. 9. Hoſea 3. 5. Nor do the <hi>Characters</hi> given him in that kind, ſpeak more then his <hi>own practiſe</hi> juſtified. Every morning, his <hi>waking thoughts converſed with God,</hi> Pſal. 139. 8. Yea, he was one, who (over and above the ſeventh day reſerved by God for his publique ſervice, which he as conſtantly attended, as the <hi>door-keepers of Gods houſe</hi> themſelves, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. 10.) conſecrated <hi>ſeven</hi> petty Sabbaths <hi>a day</hi> to devotion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 164. and broke his ſleep <hi>at midnight</hi> to ſpend time in religious duties, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 62. and one of ſo <hi>raiſed a spirit</hi> in his pious meditations and devotions, that <hi>his remains</hi> have been ever ſince made uſe of, as <hi>Forms of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Devotion</hi> in the Church, in which Notion he is called the <hi>ſweet Pſalmiſt of Iſrael,</hi> 2 Sam. 23. 1.</p>
            <p>And for the <hi>tenderneſſe of his conſcience,</hi> there needs no other <note place="margin">and notably <hi>tender-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcienced.</hi>
               </note> evidence, then (that one inſtance already touched at) the diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance he felt in himſelf for <hi>cutting off</hi> but one <hi>thred of</hi> Sauls <hi>gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:43483:19"/> though done for a <hi>teſtimony</hi> of his own <hi>innocency,</hi> 1 Sam. 24. 5.</p>
            <p>This is <hi>the perſon,</hi> whom the relation of this <hi>Amalekite,</hi> concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his murthering of <hi>Saul,</hi> doth ſo tranſport into an holy paſſion, that he cries out, <hi>How waſt thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thy hand to deſtory the Lords Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein he ſets a fair copy for all perſons who <hi>pretend to Saintſhip,</hi> and <hi>plead Tenderneſſe of Conſcience,</hi> to write after: and gives us of <hi>this Age</hi> a liberal occaſion to wonder at that <hi>new-faſhion'd,</hi> or rather <hi>new-fangled</hi> garb of <hi>Sanctity,</hi> which ſome have aſſumed to <hi>cloak</hi> the actual guilt of farre more horrid Villanies, than this (the very <hi>relation</hi> whereof ſo ſtartled <hi>David)</hi> in my <hi>Text;</hi> and at that <hi>paradoxical</hi> notion of <hi>tenderneſſe of conſcience,</hi> which admits <hi>Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Treaſons</hi> of the moſt horrid aggravation imaginable, into the reputation of moſt <hi>heroical vertues,</hi> and <hi>elevated acts of Religion.</hi> For ſurely, if <hi>David</hi> were ſuch an <hi>eminent Saint,</hi> theſe perſons who ſo directly <hi>walk Antipodes</hi> to his principles and practiſe, can paſs with all ſober Chriſtians for no other then <hi>incarnate devils:</hi> and if <hi>Davids Conſcience</hi> were ſo <hi>truly and remarkably tender,</hi> the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of <hi>theſe men</hi> muſt needs be <hi>harder than Adamants,</hi> and <hi>ſeared</hi> into an <hi>incurable dedolency,</hi> whoſe principles and tempers carry ſo irreconcileable a <hi>contradiction</hi> to his, and that in a matter of ſo high a concernment as <hi>blood,</hi> and that not of ordinary perſons, but of the <hi>Lords Anointed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider him <hi>as a King</hi> (in his <hi>politick</hi> and <hi>publick capacity,)</hi> 
               <note place="margin">In his <hi>politick Capacity</hi> (by the death of <hi>Saul) King.</hi>
               </note> which by <hi>Sauls</hi> death he was now veſted withall. The <hi>Intelligence</hi> which <hi>this Miſcreant</hi> brought him (it is probable) gave him the firſt glimpſe, the firſt intimation of the actual devolution of the <hi>Crown</hi> upon him: and now, as a <hi>publick Magiſtrate,</hi> he gives the <hi>Relator</hi> himſelf the <hi>firſt handſell</hi> of his new <hi>Royalty,</hi> a ſevere <hi>incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation</hi> in the Text, and a deſerved <hi>execution</hi> in thoſe that follow. And a like piece of Juſtice doth he (a while afterwards) execute upon the murtherers of <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> the ſon of <hi>Saul,</hi> who had for two years been ſet up by a Faction, as Competitor with him in the Kingdom, <hi>chap. 4. Examples,</hi> followed by <hi>Amaziah King of Judah,</hi> upon the murtherers of his <hi>father Joaſh,</hi> 2 King. 14. 5. and very or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarily to be paralell'd in <hi>all Hiſtories,</hi> wherein there is no piece of Juſtice more commonly taken notice of, then the ſevere inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition and recompenſe made by <hi>ſucceeding Princes,</hi> for the blood of
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43483:20"/> their <hi>Predeceſſors.</hi> And indeed, both the <hi>Law of God</hi> (which ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits <note place="margin">(Upon occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof,</note> no compenſation for <hi>humane blood,</hi> but the <hi>blood of him that ſheds it,</hi> and that upon good reaſon too, becauſe in the murther of man the <hi>Image of God</hi> is defaced, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 6.) allows and requires this ſeverity, in ſuch caſes: and the <hi>Law of man</hi> conformably al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots an <hi>exemplary addition of poenal circumſtances, to that ſeverity</hi> in the caſe of <hi>King-killing,</hi> upon weighty reaſon, ſeeing in that <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious crime</hi> there is a defacing of a <hi>double Image of God,</hi> both Natural and Political. So that if it were poſſible to inflict a <hi>dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble death</hi> upon ſuch malefactours, their <hi>double,</hi> yea, <hi>manifold</hi> guilt (for he that murthers a <hi>Supream Magiſtrate,</hi> virtually and in effect, murthers a <hi>Community)</hi> would abundantly juſtifie the rigour of ſuch an execution. <note place="margin">Juven. Sat. 8.</note>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Horum ſupplicio non debuit una parari</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Simia, non ſerpens unus, non culeus unus.</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>One death</hi> (indeed) is too little for ſuch <hi>Paricides,</hi> as kill the <hi>Father of an whole Kingdom.</hi> Severity in ſuch a caſe, is ſuch a piece of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> as <hi>eſtabliſheth the Throne</hi> (Prov. 16. 12.) by ſcaring thoſe of ſucceeding Ages from <hi>doing ſo preſumptuouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon conſideration whereof, as <hi>thoſe Princes</hi> are abundantly <note place="margin">The <hi>ſevere cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances</hi> of the execution of Traitors, juſtified.)</note> juſtified, who in this piece of juſtice follow <hi>Davids example;</hi> ſo are <hi>thoſe perſons</hi> as much to be blamed, whoſe either <hi>good nature,</hi> and <hi>ſoftneſs of diſpoſition,</hi> or <hi>evil Principles,</hi> and <hi>partnerſhip of guilt,</hi> prejudiceth them againſt the <hi>ſevere executions of Regicides,</hi> which humane Laws <hi>every where appoint,</hi> and humane Authority <hi>(in terro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem)</hi> for others terrour, <hi>ſomtimes practiſeth.</hi> For it is but meet, that <hi>exemplary ſeverity</hi> ſhould teach men the <hi>difference</hi> between the value to be put upon the perſons of <hi>Princes,</hi> and <hi>Subjects:</hi> Otherwiſe <hi>Aſſaſinations</hi> would be as frequently acted upon <hi>Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns,</hi> as <hi>Murders</hi> upon <hi>Private men;</hi> yea, hardly would any <hi>King</hi> that hath an <hi>enemy</hi> daring enough to adventure a <hi>bare life,</hi> be tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated into Heaven <hi>ſiccâ morte,</hi> with an unbloudy death. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as (on the other ſide) experience tels us, that thoſe who can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temn a <hi>ſingle death,</hi> yet dread it cloathed with ſuch <hi>Circumſtances,</hi> as carry a <hi>Brand of eternal ignominy</hi> with them, by a <hi>Blot</hi> upon the <hi>Memory,</hi> and a <hi>Tincture</hi> upon the <hi>Bloud</hi> to all poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:43483:20"/>
            <p>II. Conſider <hi>David</hi> according to the <hi>Preſumptions on which the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And as <hi>he was miſtaken</hi> by the confident Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptions of the Murderer.</note> 
               <hi>Murderer grounded his Confidence,</hi> and we ſhall find an ample Ground, for the farther improvement of his Example herein. For, if a <hi>David</hi> perſecuted by a <hi>Tyrannous King,</hi> and that without any colour of Juſtice, for ſo many years, be thus affected with the Murder of his <hi>Implacable Perſecutor,</hi> if a <hi>David,</hi> who had fled <hi>to Arms for ſhelter,</hi> againſt his <hi>Soveraigns unjuſt violence,</hi> neither dared himſelf to uſe thoſe Arms to the prejudice of <hi>his Perſon,</hi> when he had him within his power, nor would diſmiſs his <hi>actual Murderer</hi> without <hi>exemplary vengeance;</hi> and laſtly, if the <hi>undoub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted right of Succeſſion in his Throne,</hi> and the <hi>long expected news of an avoydance thereof,</hi> could not ſoften the radicated Principles of Loyalty in <hi>David,</hi> ſo far, as to induce him to admit of a ſecret ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillation of complacency in that <hi>Fact,</hi> when done to his hand, which <hi>made his way plain</hi> to the poſſeſſion of a <hi>juſt Royalty,</hi> or ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten him one jot towards the Perſon who had been the <hi>Inſtrument of making room</hi> for him: doth it not demonſtratively follow, that all <hi>other Perſons,</hi> (eſpecially ſuch as are not under the like probable <hi>Effects of Tentation</hi> in this kind) ſhould be as ſowrly irreconcilea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Agents</hi> and <hi>Principles,</hi> which are <hi>in the ſame condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> for prodigious impiety and flagitiouſneſs? Eſpecially, when it ſhall be conſidered, how <hi>emphatically,</hi> how <hi>pathetically David</hi> expreſſeth his <hi>ſenſe</hi> of this horrid action, which I ſhall lay before your conſideration in the handing of the <hi>Third</hi> and <hi>Laſt Part</hi> of my Text.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, The <hi>Quomodo,</hi> or manner of <hi>Davids Expreſſion</hi> of the <note place="margin">Part 3. <hi>Quomodo.</hi> Or the <hi>Manner</hi> how <hi>David</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.</note> violence of thoſe <hi>Paſſions,</hi> which he inwardly felt upon occaſion of this <hi>Relation;</hi> which (as I told you before) is by way of ſharp and <hi>cutting Interrogation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Importing,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Grief.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Wonder.</hi> With</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Horrour.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Grief.</hi> Which, how great it was in <hi>Davids</hi> Breaſt upon <hi>Grief.</hi> this occaſion, divers Particulars in the <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>Context</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs.</p>
            <p>And thoſe may be reduced to theſe <hi>two</hi> Heads; (Evidenced in,</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Sudden Tranſports.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Deliberate and Solemn Acts.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:43483:21"/>1. For Evidence of his <hi>ſudden Tranſports,</hi> let us but view the <note place="margin">
                  <hi>His Sudden Transports.</hi> &amp;</note> 11th. and 12th. verſes; where we are told, that he <hi>rent his cloaths,</hi> and put all his <hi>Court</hi> into a like Poſture of Mourning. <hi>He mourns, and weeps, and faſts all that day until Even.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. For evide<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce of his <hi>Deliberate and Solemn Acts,</hi> to teſtifie <note place="margin">His <hi>Deliberate and Solemn Acts.)</hi>
               </note> his hearty ſorrow for this doleful accident, we find him, <hi>v.</hi> 17, 18. (as I told you in the Preface) penning an <hi>Epicedium</hi> or Funeral-Song, for the conſtant uſe both of <hi>himſelf,</hi> and the <hi>People of Judah,</hi> and commanding it to be ſet to a Muſical <hi>Tune,</hi> and taught them; that this Lamentation might be perpetuated to all poſterity. Nor was <hi>Davids</hi> example in this kind altogether <hi>barren,</hi> for we find it afterwards followed by the <hi>godly Jews,</hi> upon occaſion of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timely death of <hi>good Joſiah;</hi> they mourned ſo truly and heartily for him, that the greatneſs of their ſorrow in after-ages grew into a Prove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>b, <hi>[as the mourning of Hadadrimmon in the Valley of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giddon,</hi> Zech. 12. 11.] And among their Solemn Lamentations, had one kept on record to Poſterity, penned by an holy Prophet, <hi>Lam. 4. 20.</hi> and perpetuated the ſolemn remembrance of that heavy ſtroak by publick Command: For ſo <hi>2 Chron.</hi> 35. 24, 25. expreſſeth it at large: <hi>All Judah and Jeruſalem mourned for Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiah; and Jeremiah lamented for Joſiah, and all the ſinging men and ſinging women ſpake of Joſiah in their Lamentations to this day, and made them an Ordiance in Iſrael, and behold, they are written in the Lamentations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And afterwards, when <hi>Gedaliah</hi> the good Governour left by <hi>Nebuzaradan,</hi> was treacherouſly ſlain by <hi>Iſhmael, Jer.</hi> 41. 1, 2. We find there was an <hi>Annual Faſt</hi> appointed, and obſerved till after the return from Captivity, upon the <hi>Moneth</hi> wherein he was ſlain, as the moſt judicious Interpreters expound the <hi>Faſt of the</hi> 7th. <hi>Moneth,</hi> Zech. 7. 5. Which Examples loudly call for <hi>like</hi> deep and ſolemn <hi>Impreſſions</hi> and <hi>Expreſſions</hi> of heartieſt ſorrow from all Loyal Subjects upon like <hi>Accidents,</hi> and abundantly ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie the <hi>Annual Solemnization</hi> of <hi>this Day;</hi> (eſpecially if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, how great a <hi>Loſſe</hi> theſe Kingdoms ſuffered, and how great a <hi>Guilt</hi> they contracted by the Lamentable Providence that occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned it: Of which, more plentifully anon. Indeed the <hi>Tears of Subjects</hi> are the beſt <hi>Spices</hi> to embalm a <hi>Soveraigns Memory</hi> withal; nor can there be a louder atteſtation to the <hi>Deſerts of a Prince,</hi> than that his <hi>Loſſe</hi> is bewailed as a <hi>Common Calamity.</hi> Upon
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:43483:21"/> which account it is, that God promiſeth it as a ſignal Mercy to the hopeful <hi>Son</hi> of wicked <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> that <hi>all Iſrael ſhould mourn for him,</hi> 1 Kings 14. 13. and threatens it as a heavy judgment on <hi>Jehoiakim,</hi> the wicked Son of good <hi>Joſiah,</hi> that he <hi>ſhould be buried with the Burial of an Aſſe,</hi> thrown in a ditch, without any <hi>one to mourn or lament for him,</hi> neither <hi>Brother,</hi> nor <hi>Siſter,</hi> nor <hi>Subject,</hi> Jer. 22. 18, 19.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Wonder</hi> and <hi>Aſtoniſhment,</hi> at the ſtrangeneſs of the accident, <note place="margin">Wonder,</note> and boldneſs of the Villain, in firſt daring to <hi>act,</hi> and then, not bluſhing to <hi>relate</hi> that fearful wickedneſs. And fit it is that ſuch <hi>Monſters</hi> wherever they are found, ſhould ſtill ſet the whole world at <hi>gaze</hi> in a pious <hi>Amazement.</hi> Which Affection, however in it ſelf it be not ſo directly <hi>moral,</hi> as ſome others are, yet it condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth very much to the exciting of that which <hi>is ſo,</hi> to wit, an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſhyneſs</hi> and <hi>averſation</hi> of mind towards thoſe <hi>Tentations,</hi> which we are before prepoſſeſſed againſt with a <hi>potent prejudice,</hi> as ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>monſtrous</hi> and <hi>portentous Births of helliſh wickedneſs:</hi> Which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions whoſoever hath, concerning the deteſtable ſin of <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>killing,</hi> will quickly improve it unto,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abomination</hi> and <hi>Abhorrency:</hi> the third Paſſion, wherein <hi>David</hi> expreſſeth his ſenſe of this horrid Fact. For we may very <note place="margin">and <hi>Horrour</hi> or <hi>Abomination</hi>
               </note> well ſuppoſe that his <hi>tender</hi> and <hi>delicate Conſcience</hi> preſently took an <hi>Alarm</hi> from the <hi>Amalekites</hi> brazen-faced <hi>Relation,</hi> and <hi>rallied</hi> all the Spirits in his Body, to the <hi>Fort-Royal of his Heart,</hi> to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie it againſt the <hi>peſtilential breath</hi> of ſuch a <hi>proditious Monſter;</hi> and thence it ſhot forth the <hi>Darts</hi> of fiery indignation in the <hi>Frowns of his Royal Countenance,</hi> and ſharpned every <hi>hair of his head</hi> into a <hi>Porcupines Quill,</hi> which extream horrour erected (as it were of purpoſe) to fly in the <hi>Face</hi> of the <hi>detestable Object.</hi> All this, and more, preſents it ſelfe to our apprehenſion, in the Form of this <hi>ſtinging Interrogation,</hi> wherein, <hi>Quot Verba, Tot Tonitrua;</hi> every word is a Clap of Thunder, <hi>How wast thou not afraid to ſtretch forth thy hand to deſtroy the Lords Anointed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, nothing leſſe than ſuch an <hi>Hyperbold of abomination</hi> will ſerve to expreſs, as it ought, the <hi>juſt ſenſe</hi> which thoſe who will imitate <hi>David</hi> in either of his forementioned Capaci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies, (whether of <hi>good men</hi> or <hi>good Magiſtrates)</hi> ought to have of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that monſtrous <hi>ſteam</hi> of <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>ſtench</hi> of the <hi>bottomleſs Pit,</hi> which breaths out of the mouths of thoſe <hi>unclean</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:43483:22"/> 
               <hi>Beaſts,</hi> and <hi>Lying Prophets, (whoſe Throats</hi> are worſe than <hi>an open Sepulcher)</hi> by whom the ſin of <hi>King-killing</hi> (which <hi>David</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good man ſo ſtartles at) is not only proclaimed <hi>Lawful,</hi> but extolled as <hi>meritorious;</hi> and much more, of that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Abomination of Deſolation,</hi> (the <hi>practiſe</hi> of that monſtrous <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple)</hi> when (eſpecially) it ſhall be <hi>ſet up in the holy place,</hi> and <hi>wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped</hi> in the thoughts of deluded Creatures, as a <hi>diſtinguiſhing Character of eminent holineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus (at laſt, have I done with the <hi>Text,</hi> as it relates to <note n="2" place="margin">II. <hi>Seco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d View</hi> of the <hi>Text.</hi> As <hi>accomoda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> to the <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Chapter</hi> and <hi>Narrative</hi> contained in it, together with the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> and <hi>Inferences</hi> (in general) comprehended therein. It on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remains, that I <hi>review</hi> them in this place, as they may be <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comodated</hi> by way of <hi>Parallel</hi> to the ſad <hi>occaſion of this daies Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly, when I thought of finding out a <hi>parallel Text of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Parallel</hi> relating to the <hi>Parts</hi> of the Text.</note> 
               <hi>Scripture</hi> to the <hi>Text of Providence,</hi> which this ſad day cals to our Remembrance, I muſt confeſſe, I found my ſelf ar an unu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual loſs. <hi>Many Kings</hi> deaths are recorded in Sacred Writ, and divers of them <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>bloudy;</hi> and divers of them <hi>brought about</hi> by the hands of <hi>Rebellious</hi> and <hi>Traiterous Subjects.</hi> But to match all the Circumſtances of the <hi>moſt execrable Murder</hi> of our <hi>Late Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraign,</hi> I know none that can tolerably pretend un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it.</p>
            <p>That which my Text attempts towards it, lies rather in the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel <note place="margin">In the <hi>Firſt,</hi> (expreſſing the <hi>Horridneſs of the Sin.)</hi>
               </note> which ſhould be between <hi>Davids Spirit</hi> and <hi>ours,</hi> upon ſo ſad an occaſion (for which end mainly I made choice of it) then that which may be ſuppoſed between <hi>Sauls Perſon</hi> and <hi>Death</hi> and his <hi>Majeſties,</hi> which are (almoſt altogether) <hi>unparallelable.</hi> And therefore in thoſe ſhort <hi>Touches of Collation,</hi> which I ſhall beſtow upon them, I muſt of neceſſity compare them, and what befell them, in their <hi>diſcrepancies;</hi> as that <hi>Painter,</hi> who to ſet off the vaſt bigneſs of an <hi>Elephant,</hi> draws a <hi>Mouſe</hi> by his ſide.</p>
            <p>It is true indeed, that in <hi>ſome of the aggravations</hi> of the horrid <note place="margin">How far it <hi>holds:</hi> &amp; VVhere it <hi>halts,</hi> viz.</note> murder committed upon them <hi>both,</hi> the <hi>Parallel holds.</hi> That <hi>both</hi> were <hi>Kings, Anointed,</hi> and the <hi>Lords Anointed,</hi> and <hi>both murder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Subjects;</hi> but the <hi>differences</hi> are far more in the reſt of the Circumſtances, and thoſe ſo <hi>vaſt,</hi> that the power of Invention c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n hardly bring them nearer to one another, than the <hi>two Poles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:43483:22"/>1. Conſider we the <hi>Perſon Murdered</hi> (our Late <hi>Gracious,</hi> and <note place="margin">In the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the <hi>Perſons</hi> murdered; King <hi>Saul</hi> &amp; King <hi>Charles.</hi> (Occaſioning a ſhort <hi>Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter</hi> of our <hi>late Soveraign.)</hi>
               </note> now <hi>Glorious Soveraign.</hi> A perſon (take him either as <hi>Man,</hi> or <hi>King)</hi> of a Temper ſo far different from <hi>Sauls,</hi> that as the one ſeemed to be compoſed of <hi>Cruelty,</hi> ſo the other ſeemed to have nothing in his Conſtitution but <hi>Clemency.</hi> A perſon (in both capacities, both of <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>King)</hi> ſo free, not only from the <hi>guilt,</hi> but even from the <hi>ſuſpition</hi> of any enormous Crime, that the malice of his Accuſers themſelves, could find nothing to ſtuffe out that <hi>Black Charge</hi> which they laid againſt him, but the <hi>unhappy Conteſts</hi> between <hi>Himſelf</hi> and his <hi>Subjects</hi> (the ſad Iſſues of <hi>mutu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Jealouſies,</hi> blown up into an <hi>open War</hi> by a Divine <hi>Blaſt</hi> upon <hi>all thoſe Counſels,</hi> which might have <hi>prevented</hi> it, and a juſt immiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of an <hi>evil Spirit of Perverſities to mingle with them,</hi> and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them ineffectual, for the juſt puniſhment of our <hi>ſins)</hi> which indeed were his <hi>Infelicity,</hi> but their <hi>guilt,</hi> who firſt made the Breach, and afterwards (as much as in them lay) hindred the <hi>making it up,</hi> becauſe their own Conſcience of having unpardona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offended him, told them, they could expect no <hi>Security,</hi> but in his <hi>Ruine.</hi> A Perſon and <hi>King,</hi> of ſo elevated a ſize, both for <hi>Intellectual</hi> and <hi>Moral</hi> Endowments, that the ſtature of his <hi>inward man,</hi> as much overtopped the moſt accompliſhed of his Subjects, as <hi>Sauls outward man</hi> did overlook the reſt of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> 1 Sam. 10. 23.</p>
            <p>For his <hi>Intellectuals:</hi> He was endowed with ſuch an height of <hi>Phancy,</hi> as would have won him the <hi>Laurel</hi> in a Commonwealth of <hi>Poets.</hi> He was Maſter of ſo ſublime a <hi>Grandeur</hi> of Language, and ſtately <hi>Majesticalneſs,</hi> joyned with an amiable fluency of <hi>Style,</hi> as might have challenged a <hi>Dictatorſhip</hi> among the beſt of <hi>Orators;</hi> of which his <hi>Royal Remains</hi> are an indiſputable evidence. And for <hi>Soundneſs of Judgment,</hi> both in Points of <hi>Controverſie,</hi> and Caſes of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> he might have challenged the <hi>Theological Chair,</hi> upon the account of meer worth, and have ſate not only <hi>Regius Profeſſor,</hi> but <hi>Rex Profeſſorum,</hi> in both <hi>Univerſities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For his <hi>Morals:</hi> He was <hi>Juſt, Valiant, Temperate, Chaſt, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciful</hi> (and what not?) to ſuch a proportion, as he might have ſet the beſt of his Subjects a Copy of vertue in his own example.</p>
            <p>Indeed he was a <hi>Prince</hi> who might have paſſed clear with the univerſal reputation of the beſt of <hi>Engliſh Kings,</hi> had he not faln into the <hi>worſt of Times,</hi> wherein the <hi>Engliſh Manners</hi> were ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:43483:23"/> with the blandiſhments of a long continued tranquillity and plenty; and their <hi>judgements</hi> ſo intoxicated with prejudice, and cenſoriouſneſſe, that too too many neither <hi>loved</hi> the <hi>practiſe</hi> of vertue themſelves, nor would willingly <hi>allow</hi> the <hi>reputation</hi> of it to others.</p>
            <p>A <hi>King,</hi> whom if we had not by our ſins rendred our ſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy to <hi>enjoy</hi> longer, we had been (it may be to this day) in danger of nothing more then being <hi>ſurfeited</hi> with our own <hi>felicity.</hi> And that we <hi>enjoyed him not,</hi> all the world muſt bear him witneſs, it was not <hi>his fault,</hi> ſeeing in that <hi>laſt</hi> and <hi>fatall Treaty</hi> (as Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence made it) at <hi>Newport,</hi> he ſhewed ſo great a deſire in his <hi>Gracious Condeſcenſions</hi> to <hi>make his people happy,</hi> that he even forgot he had <hi>any ſhare of his own</hi> to challenge among them; having in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>given</hi> them <hi>all,</hi> but (what he could not part with) that <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign goodneſſe</hi> of diſpoſition, which was the only thing (almoſt) that he had left, beſides the redintigrated <hi>affections of his people,</hi> (di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of whom began then to <hi>know</hi> him <hi>better,</hi> and therefore <hi>valued</hi> him the <hi>more,</hi> out of conviction that they had ignorantly perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted him) to ſupport his <hi>Throne</hi> withall. So that, I muſt needs ſay it was the <hi>fatall infatuation,</hi> and <hi>infelicity</hi> of theſe Nations, that <hi>they knew not in the day of their viſitation the things that belonged to their peace:</hi> and therefore were they (by the righteous judgement of God) for a full <hi>decad</hi> of years and <hi>more,</hi> juſtly <hi>hid from their eyes.</hi>
               <q>
                  <hi>O fortunatos nimium bona ſi ſua nôſſent Anglicolas!</hi>—</q>
            </p>
            <p>And for his <hi>Religion,</hi> This I think may ſafely be ſaid without exception from any, but ſuch as all <hi>Religions</hi> may bluſh to <hi>own,</hi> that if the imployment of his <hi>ſerener hours</hi> were of a piece with the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of his <hi>Solitudes and Sufferings;</hi> that man is not <hi>enough Chriſtian</hi> himſelf, who can admit a diſpute in his own boſom, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ought not to be ranked among the <hi>chiefeſt of Chriſtians:</hi> or, if (as ſome ſuppoſe) his <hi>Afflictions</hi> were the <hi>School</hi> wherein he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the <hi>firſt elements</hi> of <hi>practical Piety,</hi> this (in deed and truth) is ſo far from being a <hi>diſparagement</hi> to him, that it renders him ſo much more the <hi>ſubject</hi> of all good mens <hi>admiration</hi> and <hi>aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for making ſo wonderfull a proficiency in ſo ſhort a time, as the digeſting into practice the whole Doctrine and Example of his
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:43483:23"/> 
               <hi>Maſter Chriſt,</hi> and eſpecially ſo much as related to the <hi>laſt paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges</hi> of his life, proclaims to all the world.</p>
            <p>And if in ſome <hi>modes</hi> and other <hi>circumſtantials</hi> of his <hi>Profeſſion,</hi> he pleaſed not <hi>all men,</hi> yea poſſibly might diſtaſte ſome <hi>good men;</hi> yet (even in theſe) his <hi>conſcientious constancy</hi> (and no other prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple could prevail with him, when all his earthly enjoyments were apparently adventured to a deſperate irrecoverableneſſe by his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hering to them) ought not to be <hi>diſpleaſing</hi> to <hi>any.</hi> Eſpecially when we conſider, how many <hi>principles</hi> and <hi>practiſes</hi> of far <hi>greater incompatibility</hi> with <hi>true piety,</hi> muſt be allowed, to make the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of <hi>ſome</hi> perſons currant, who moſt diſparage <hi>His.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And indeed, whatever we thought of him <hi>living</hi> (as to his <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,)</hi> the conſequences of his <hi>death</hi> too ſadly evidenced, how much the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe</hi> was concerned in his <hi>preſervation:</hi> and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, the ſad face of this <hi>Orphan-Church of ours,</hi> which from that time forwards, became the lamentableſt ſcene of <hi>Anarchy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> that ever was ſeen in the <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> not excepting <hi>Munſter</hi> it ſelf, that ſaw but the <hi>prologue</hi> to our <hi>Tragedy.</hi> For who knows not, that whatever <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Parties</hi> ſtepped up into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s vacant Seat, made it the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſter-piece of their <hi>policy</hi> (like ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeking Chirurgions) to keep our <hi>wounds</hi> open, that they might keep <hi>themſelves</hi> in <hi>practiſe:</hi> and to maintain oppoſite Factions to peck at <hi>one another,</hi> that whiles the people were buſied in <hi>private contests,</hi> they might be the leſſe ſenſible of their <hi>publique oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> Inſomuch, that the ſad revival of <hi>old Hereſies</hi> and <hi>Schiſmes</hi> (every one of which carried a <hi>Legion</hi> of <hi>new ones</hi> in its belly) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the apparent <hi>dangers of extirpation</hi> to the <hi>true Protestant Religion,</hi> and all its <hi>Profeſsors,</hi> for many years together ſince our ſins removed Him from us, have <hi>convinced</hi> not a few, that he was not ſo much to blame, as was too commonly thought, for not giving His conſent to thoſe <hi>violent</hi> and <hi>ſudden changes</hi> which their <hi>miſguided zeal</hi> (among many others alike miſ-led,) in thoſe times too importunately <hi>called for.</hi> And no doubt, if he had lived to have perfected his own deſigned <hi>Modell</hi> for the <hi>Churches ſettlement,</hi> moſt of thoſe <hi>diſſentions</hi> that have been of late (and yet are) too <hi>flagrant</hi> among us, had long before they arrived at this <hi>maturity,</hi> been buried in the <hi>grave of oblivion,</hi> not ſo much by <hi>ſuppreſſing,</hi> as by <hi>reconciling</hi> the Diſſenters. But, as <hi>David</hi> when he had colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted <hi>materials</hi> for the building of the <hi>Temple,</hi> was fain to <hi>leave<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:43483:24"/> them with his Advice and Benediction to his <hi>Son Solomon</hi> to make uſe of: So our <hi>Gracious Soveraign,</hi> being not permitted by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to live to ſee the <hi>Rearing</hi> of that <hi>Structure,</hi> which he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, hath left ſuch <hi>Materials</hi> behind him, together with his Fatherly <hi>Charge</hi> and <hi>Bleſſing,</hi> for this happy work, to his <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuine Son</hi> and <hi>Lawful Succeſſor, our preſent Gracious King</hi> (whom God long preſerve) that we no waies doubt, but (as they are wonderful ſutable to the Moderation of his <hi>Majesties</hi> temper, ſo) they will in due time be ſucceſſefully made uſe of by him to the Happy Settlement of <hi>theſe Churches</hi> with the infinite <hi>Contentment</hi> of all thoſe that <hi>love the Peace of Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the mean while, if by what I have ſaid concerning the <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> whoſe <hi>Funeral Anniverſary,</hi> this Day is appointed to ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize (and I am afraid I have rather injur'd his <hi>Memory,</hi> by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>too little,</hi> than the <hi>Truth,</hi> by ſaying <hi>too much</hi> of him) you be in any meaſure ſenſible of the <hi>Loſs</hi> you ſuffered by his violent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval, I hope you are the better prepared to entertain the <hi>next Conſideration,</hi> wherein this <hi>accurſed Paricide</hi> exceeded that of <hi>Saul</hi> in my <hi>Text;</hi> and that is,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The View of the <hi>Perſons who committed this horrid Act:</hi> And <note place="margin">As alſo in the difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Murderers of both.</note> here our <hi>Parallel halts</hi> again. Had they been <hi>Native Forreigners,</hi> as the <hi>Amalekite</hi> in my <hi>Text</hi> was, and as he was (in probability) educated in a <hi>Heathen Religion,</hi> and ſowred with the Leaven of <hi>National Enmity,</hi> heightned with the provocation of an <hi>univerſal Maſſacre,</hi> acted by the perſon they ſo barbarouſly murdered, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all their <hi>deareſt Relations,</hi> the <hi>Crime</hi> had been <hi>more pardonable;</hi> but theſe <hi>Paricides</hi> were his <hi>Majesties Native Subjects,</hi> that had drawn their <hi>firſt Breath</hi> in his <hi>Hereditary Dominions,</hi> &amp; to this <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Bond of Allegiance,</hi> had voluntarily added divers ſtronger Tyes of <hi>religious Oaths, Proteſtations and Covenants;</hi> yea, ſome of thoſe that <hi>lifted up</hi> not their <hi>Heels</hi> only, but their <hi>Hands</hi> againſt him, were ſuch as did eat of his <hi>Bread,</hi> his own <hi>ſworn Servants,</hi> none of them <hi>diſobliged</hi> by any ſuch <hi>Provocations of cruel Uſages,</hi> ſo that it is hard to imagine, how it might be poſſible to load a Malefactor with more <hi>perſonal aggravating Conſiderations,</hi> to render him <hi>monſtrouſly criminal,</hi> than theſe were notoriouſly guilty of; except only, that <hi>one</hi> (which like a vaſt <hi>Mountain,</hi> overtops all the reſt) that they were Perſons of the <hi>Profeſsed True Religion,</hi> and in that Profeſſion, coveted to engroſs the Reputation of the moſt <hi>eminently ſtrict and</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:43483:24"/> 
               <hi>Conſcientious.</hi> And indeed, this is an aggravation, which ought be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond all others, to <hi>whet the indignation</hi> of every Conſcientious Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian to a <hi>keenneſs</hi> beyond all moderation, as that which is moſt <hi>highly injurious</hi> to the whole <hi>Reformed Cauſe</hi> throughout all the vvorld. O <hi>tell it not in Gath, nor publiſh it in the ſtreets of Askalon, leſt the Daughters of the Philiſtines rejoyce!</hi> Alas! What <hi>sport</hi> hath this <note place="margin">V. 20.</note> ſad ſcandal already made, and hovv much more may it yet make, to the <hi>Romiſh Emiſſaries,</hi> vvhoſe <hi>Religion</hi> hath been vvonted to raiſe <hi>Rebellions,</hi> and to canonize for <hi>Saints,</hi> the moſt prodigious <hi>Traytors;</hi> and hath alone born the <hi>odium</hi> of monopolizing the <note place="margin">(Occaſioning a <hi>Vindication</hi> of the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>igion</hi> from <hi>Romiſh Calumn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>s.)</hi>
               </note> guilt of <hi>murdering Princes,</hi> for many ages; that they have novv too colourable a pretence to diſcharge a part of that guilt upon thoſe of the <hi>Proteſtant Communion,</hi> as being hereby become <hi>Fratres in malo,</hi> Brethren in this horrid vvickedneſs vvith themſelves! An <hi>Occaſion</hi> vvhich vve confeſs vve have cauſe to bevvail, becauſe they make <hi>ſuch uſe</hi> of it: But vve muſt vvithal tell them, that vve think our <hi>Profeſſion</hi> no vvay touched in its <hi>reputation</hi> thereby, in the judgment of any vvhom <hi>inveterate Malice</hi> doth not preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate againſt us. For beſides, that the <hi>Perſons</hi> ingaged in this <hi>horrid Act,</hi> vvere (moſt of them) departed from the <hi>Proteſtant Faith</hi> or <hi>Communion,</hi> or both, before they ingaged in this <hi>horrid Villany,</hi> (and ſo can no more juſtly reflect the guilt thereof up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Church they once belonged to, than a <hi>Renegado</hi>'s miſcarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages can concern the <hi>Troop</hi> vvhich he hath forſaken) Let the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt</hi> knovv, that no ſuch <hi>Fruit</hi> ever grevv upon the <hi>root</hi> of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Doctrines,</hi> vvhich abhor and deteſt all ſuch Principles, and execrate all ſuch Offenders; and (by conſequence) if any perſons vvho profeſſed themſelves <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> vvere guilty of this <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Fact, Proteſtancy</hi> it ſelf is no more concerned in it, than any State is in the Crimes of other Malefactors, vvho ſuffer daily by the Svvord of Juſtice, for <hi>Robberies, Murders,</hi> and <hi>Burglaries,</hi> vvithout any imputation upon the Community to vvhich they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long; vvhich ſufficiently vindicates it ſelf, by the <hi>Laws</hi> provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded againſt ſuch Crimes, and the <hi>Severity</hi> executed upon thoſe vvho commit them, from any partnerſhip in them.</p>
            <p>In a word, when the <hi>Romaniſt</hi> can ſhew us any ſuch <hi>Tenets</hi> as theſe, publickly avowed by <hi>general conſent of Proteſtants,</hi> [That <hi>Chriſt hath left a power to any Perſon or Perſons in his Church to diſpoſe of all Crowns and Scepters, and hath ſubordinated the Temporal to the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ual
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:43483:25"/> Sword: And that Soveraign Princes being once blaſted by the Thunderbolts of that Church, may be lawfully depoſed and murdered by their Subjects; and that Subjects (in ſuch a caſe) are abſolved from all Oaths of Fealty and Allegiance to them,</hi> &amp;c.] let them impute the guilt of this horrid Crime to us, and ſpare not: but ſo long as we, and they notoriouſly know, <hi>whoſe Doctrines</hi> theſe are, it is no hard matter to gueſs, <hi>what Heifer</hi> thoſe Seditious Seminaries <hi>ploughed with,</hi> and at whoſe <hi>Forge</hi> they ſharpned their <hi>Goads,</hi> and <hi>Plow-ſhares,</hi> who <hi>ſowed</hi> the <hi>Tares,</hi> of ſuch <hi>Traiterous Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> in the field of our <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> and <hi>Commonwealth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However (for our fuller vindication in this Particular) let every true <hi>Proteſtant</hi> for ever abominate the <hi>Memory</hi> of thoſe Monſters, and deteſt their <hi>Principles,</hi> who have thus opened the mouths of our <hi>Adverſaries</hi> againſt our <hi>Religion,</hi> and laid ſuch a ſtumbling-block of prejudice in the way of thoſe poor ſeduced crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures among us, who are thereby hardned in the diſtance they keep from us and our Communion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. A <hi>Third Conſideration</hi> to amplifie the horrid murder of our <note place="margin">And the vaſt <hi>disproportion</hi> between the <hi>Facts them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Late Soveraign,</hi> beyond that of <hi>Saul,</hi> may be taken from <hi>the Fact it ſelf:</hi> Which although (in the caſe of <hi>Saul)</hi> it hath already been charged with,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Bloudineſs. 2. Wilfulneſs.</hi> And 3. <hi>Audacionſneſs</hi> enough: Yet in <hi>all theſe,</hi> our part of the <hi>Parallel</hi> weighs much heavier than that. The <hi>Amalekites Fact</hi> was a <hi>Sneaking Buſineſs,</hi> acted in a <hi>Corner,</hi> ſo that it had not been known, but by his own Relation. But this was a <hi>Publick Tragedy,</hi> in all the Acts of it, wherein the <hi>Conſpirators,</hi> made all the world <hi>Spectators</hi> of their <hi>audacious Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frontery.</hi> Here was a <hi>Pageantry of Publick Juſtice,</hi> an <hi>High Court</hi> ſolemnly convened, a <hi>Bench,</hi> and a <hi>Bar,</hi> a <hi>Preſident,</hi> and a <hi>Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner,</hi> an <hi>Inditement,</hi> and a <hi>Proſecution,</hi> and a <hi>Sentence,</hi> and all theſe, in the moſt publick place of Judicature in the three Nations. And after this, a <hi>Bloudy Execution,</hi> not in a <hi>Corner,</hi> but in the <hi>open Street,</hi> in the <hi>Face of the Sun,</hi> as if they meant (with a kind of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce to <hi>God himſelf)</hi> to call him in, as a publick Spectator, to behold how inſolently they trampled upon his <hi>Authority,</hi> in his undoubted <hi>Vicegerent.</hi> A <hi>Tragedy,</hi> which in all the <hi>Acts</hi> and <hi>Scenes</hi> of it, I am confident all the <hi>Hiſtories</hi> in the world cannot match. Many <hi>Kings</hi> have died by the <hi>Sword,</hi> by the <hi>Dagger</hi> and the <hi>Piſtol;</hi> many by <hi>poyſonous Drugs,</hi> and other ſuch Inſtruments
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:43483:25"/> of <hi>private</hi> and clandeſtine ambition, or revenge: But never <hi>any</hi> till this black day, by the <hi>Executioners Axe,</hi> upon a <hi>publick Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold,</hi> in the <hi>Front</hi> of His own <hi>Royal Palace, &amp;c.</hi> Nay more, if a Survey were made of all the <hi>Utopian Inventions</hi> of <hi>Poetical Fancy,</hi> no <hi>Stage</hi> ever had a <hi>Tragedy</hi> like this <hi>acted</hi> upon it. No <hi>Fabulous or feigned Hiſtory</hi> ever adventured a <hi>Relation</hi> like it to the eyes of the world: And indeed ſober Readers would have diſguſted them, if they had, upon the very account of the <hi>monſtrouſneſs</hi> of it, and taxed the Author with an unpardonable Errour, for tranſgreſſing <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ficta volupta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis cauſae ſint proxima veris. Nec quodcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> volet, poſcat ſibi fabula cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di.</hi> Hor. <hi>Art. Poet.</hi>
               </note> the ordinary Rule of Fiction, the <hi>ſubject matter</hi> whereof, muſt be ſuch as ſeems to carry an <hi>appearance of Truth,</hi> and though it be not <hi>verum,</hi> yet it is <hi>veriſimile.</hi> So that here was a <hi>confluence</hi> of all that <hi>wilful</hi> projected <hi>Cruelty</hi> and <hi>Inſolence</hi> could contribute to the aggravation of a Villany.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To ſhew the <hi>Parallel</hi> yet more <hi>unparallel,</hi> in the caſe of our <hi>late Soveraign,</hi> his Murderers had <hi>none</hi> of all thoſe <hi>Pleas</hi> to excuſe their wickedneſs, which before have been urged on the behalf of the <hi>Amalekite.</hi> For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. They made it <hi>too publick</hi> to render it any way diſputable, <note place="margin">
                  <hi>None</hi> of the <hi>Amalekites Pleas, pleada<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> for <hi>this.</hi>
               </note> whether <hi>they were the Perſons</hi> who did the Fact or no. And after they had done it, they <hi>gloried</hi> in it as an act of <hi>Tranſcendent Justice,</hi> and took pride to be <hi>pointed at</hi> for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>So far</hi> was our <hi>murdered Soveraign</hi> from being (as <hi>Saul</hi> was) a <hi>Tyrant</hi> and a <hi>Murderer;</hi> that none ever loſt <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Limb</hi> by his <hi>Authority,</hi> but in a <hi>courſe of Juſtice,</hi> or by the <hi>chance of war.</hi> And if he were an <hi>Enemy</hi> to any true <hi>Davids</hi> (which ſome object to him as a Crime) it was his <hi>Infelicity</hi> not to <hi>underſtand</hi> them to be <hi>ſuch,</hi> which occaſioned it; and I am confident, if any ſuch there be, who had cauſe to complain of hard uſage from him, they are ſo far <hi>Davids</hi> ſtill, that they will give the Murderers as <hi>little thanks</hi> for <hi>reſcuing</hi> them from their Sufferings, in <hi>ſuch a way,</hi> as he did this <hi>Amalekite.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>So far</hi> was he from being <hi>weary of his Life,</hi> and deſiring the <hi>courteſie of a dispatch</hi> out of it, that he ſtrongly and unanſwerably aſſerted to the faces of his Murderers his <hi>Right</hi> both to his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>So far</hi> was he from an <hi>inevitable neceſſity of dying</hi> at that time, either by <hi>natural Infirmity,</hi> or accidental <hi>stroak of Providence,</hi> that he was in the very <hi>Prime of his Age, Health</hi> and <hi>Strength.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:43483:26"/>5. <hi>So far</hi> was he from being <hi>purſued by any Enemies</hi> but them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that he had but newly concluded a <hi>reconciling Treaty</hi> with thoſe who had fought againſt him, whoſe <hi>Arms</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> were with a wonderful alacrity <hi>open</hi> to receive him, and <hi>expiate</hi> all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>unkindneſſes</hi> with all poſſible Demonſtrations of <hi>Affectionate Loyalty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>So far</hi> were his Murderers from <hi>lighting occaſionally upon a tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to this Fact, and being <hi>ſurprized by the unexpectedneſs</hi> thereof, that it was the iſſue of a Conſpiracy of <hi>divers years</hi> before.</p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>So far</hi> were they from being clear of the <hi>deſign of enriching themſelves with the Royal Spoyles,</hi> that (like <hi>Ahab)</hi> they had no ſooner <hi>killed,</hi> but they preſently fell to <hi>taking poſſeſſion</hi> of all the <hi>Royal Lands</hi> and <hi>Revenews,</hi> and diſtributed them amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves: And whereas this <hi>Amalekite,</hi> after he had done the Fact, he took the <hi>Crown</hi> and <hi>Bracelet of Saul,</hi> &amp; returned them to his <hi>Lawful Succeſſor;</hi> theſe barbarous Murderers to make good their un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt poſſeſſion) exclude his undoubted <hi>Heir</hi> and <hi>Succeſſor,</hi> for many years, from his <hi>unqueſtionable Rights,</hi> and put <hi>God himſelf</hi> to the expenſe of a <hi>Miracle</hi> at laſt to reſtore him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. And Laſtly, <hi>So</hi> far were they from <hi>bewailing the Fact, when they had done it,</hi> that (as I before told you) they <hi>triumphed</hi> in it, as the moſt <hi>Righteous, Heroick</hi> and <hi>Meritorious Act,</hi> that ever was done by men. And ſome-of them expreſſed an ambition to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuate the memory of their Names by no other <hi>Epitaph;</hi> yea, when Gods <hi>Juſtice</hi> and mans overtook them, and brought them to deſerved <hi>Execution,</hi> took the Confidence to challenge a <hi>Crown of</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Concluſion</hi> in a ſerious <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication</hi> of the other two <hi>parts</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a defi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e that in theſe the <hi>Parallel</hi> may hold be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>David</hi> and <hi>us:</hi> Or rather that we may <hi>excced</hi> him (as there is great cauſe)</note> 
               <hi>Martyrdom</hi> in the Kingdom of Glory, and prefer the <hi>Cauſe</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they ſuffered, before <hi>thoſe of the chiefeſt of Martyrs;</hi> and abuſed themſelves with a Rodomantick perſwaſion, that <hi>it were a piece of ambition, becoming the moſt eminont of that noble Society, to deſire an Exchange of condition with them.</hi> The ſaddeſt Inſtances of the <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficacy of deluſion</hi> that ever the world ſaw from its firſt Creation to that very day.</p>
            <p>And thus have I done with my <hi>Parallel</hi> ſo far as it concerns the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of the two <hi>Facts,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> of the <hi>Text,</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> of the <hi>Time;</hi> wherein there is little to be ſeen, but <hi>Concordia diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oors,</hi> an <hi>agreement</hi> in nothing but <hi>this,</hi> that there is <hi>ſcarce any Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance wherein they agree.</hi> I have only this to add, that I hope to find a <hi>better Harmony</hi> in the <hi>other Part</hi> of it, which comes now
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:43483:26"/> to hand; [the <hi>Parallel</hi> of <hi>Davids carriage</hi> upon the <hi>one,</hi> and the <hi>Temper</hi> of all <hi>Religious Hearts</hi> among us, and the Generations that are to come, in reference to the <hi>other]</hi> containing the <hi>due ſenſe</hi> which as <hi>he had,</hi> ſo <hi>we ought to have,</hi> of ſo deteſtable and pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acular a Fact, and diſmal a Providence: Which <hi>ſenſe</hi> (according to the forementioned diſtribution) ought to expreſs it ſelf in <hi>three</hi> things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Grief;</hi> of which <hi>David</hi> had far <hi>leſs</hi> cauſe than we, upon a <note place="margin">In our <hi>Grief,</hi> For the <hi>Loſs recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>fourfold</hi> account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the <hi>Loſs received:</hi> Which (in <hi>Davids</hi> caſe) was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderable, if compared with <hi>ours,</hi> He indeed loſt a <hi>Soveraign,</hi> valiant enough <hi>to fight the Lords Battels,</hi> and one, who by his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, had divers times <hi>ſaved Iſrael;</hi> but one who was now in his <hi>Wane</hi> and <hi>Declination;</hi> ſo that (whatſoever <hi>David</hi> in modeſty thought of him) the <hi>Loſs of Saul</hi> was <hi>Iſraels gain,</hi> by making room for a better Succeſſor, <hi>himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But <hi>our loſs</hi> was like the dropping of a <hi>skilful Pilot</hi> overboard, when the <hi>Ship</hi> under his conduct, was in the very <hi>Mouth of the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> and big with expectation of <hi>landing</hi> its precious Merchandiſe, but (by that ſad accident) caſt into the hands of <hi>raw,</hi> and <hi>raſh</hi> and <hi>mutinous Seamen;</hi> whoſe indiſcretions and animoſities have caſt us back again into a <hi>tempeſtuous Sea,</hi> where we have for many years been <hi>toſſed up and down,</hi> with unſpeakable hazard, till at laſt God by a Miraculous Providence, brought to our help, a <hi>Phoenix raiſed out</hi> of his <hi>Aſhes,</hi> the <hi>true Heir,</hi> both of his <hi>Kingdoms</hi> and <hi>Vertues,</hi> who hath once more brought us within <hi>ſight of Land,</hi> and we hope will (if our ſins obſtruct not his endeavours) <hi>ſet us ſafe on ſhore.</hi> To prevent which miſchief, we ought to <hi>grieve</hi> (as we have cauſe) more then <hi>David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Upon account of <hi>thoſe ſins</hi> (in general) which provoked <note place="margin">and <hi>our ſins</hi> (in general) pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voking God to inflict it. (VVhereof ſome are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed; (the peoples.)</note> God to take him from us. <hi>David</hi> k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ew, that God had <hi>caſt off</hi> formerly, and now <hi>out off Saul</hi> for his <hi>own</hi> ſins, not <hi>his.</hi> But we have cauſe enough to charge this loſſe upon <hi>our own provoking ſins,</hi> which (at that time, and ſince) have been too notoriouſly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent to God and the world: Such as, <hi>Contempt of Gods Word and Sacraments, Reproaching and perſecuting his Faithful Meſſengers, Wanton affecting of new Notions and Inventions, and contemning old Truths, and the primitive ſimplicity of the Gospel, Uncharitable ſchiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and ſeparations in the Church, and ambitious ſelf-ſeeking,</hi> and (in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:43483:27"/> order thereunto, <hi>fomenting Factions in the State, Sacrilegious rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of God, and barbarous spoyling and deſtroying one another with a rage</hi> reaching up to Heaven, <hi>Notorious Debauchery and Prophaneſs in all ſorts and degrees of men, which ſpared neither Gods Name, nor his Sabbaths, nor his Creatures, nor the Profeſſion of Religion in the life and power of it, toleration of Popery, and other dangerous Errors and Hereſies,</hi> and (to make our Ephah of ſins yet fuller) a <hi>spirit of Rebellion</hi> ſpread over the whole Nation, againſt <hi>juſt and lawful Authority;</hi> and many more might be added to this <hi>Black Roll,</hi> but that I haſten to an end.</p>
            <p>And was it not time (think you) for God to be <hi>avenged of ſuch a Nation as this</hi> was? and I would to God (I could with a clear Conſcience) ſtop at <hi>was:</hi> But I fear, it may, with too much evidence of Truth be added, and <hi>yet is.</hi> And who could tax that Juſtice, which by his Providence ſuffered us to <hi>cut</hi> through that <hi>Bank</hi> with our own hands, which (under himſelf) kept out that <hi>Deluge of Miſeries,</hi> which our ſins deſerved, and <hi>fell down</hi> that <hi>Royal Tree,</hi> in the <hi>Branches</hi> whereof our ſeveral <hi>Neſts</hi> were <hi>built.</hi> And oh! Let us fear, leſt by the continued guilt of the <hi>ſame ſins,</hi> we procure a <hi>Decree of the Watchers,</hi> to cut down thoſe <hi>Royal ſhoots,</hi> that have grown up in his ſtead (and he hath begun with them already, to our ſad loſſe) and not leave ſo much as a <hi>ſtump</hi> in the earth, out of which a <hi>Rod</hi> may grow, to <hi>make a Scepter</hi> of.</p>
            <p>But (poſſibly) here I may be interrupted with a <hi>Queſtion:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">The <hi>Thronts</hi> waved,</note> 
               <hi>all the Fault which provoked God to inflict ſuch a ſevere ſtroak, were in the People, and the</hi> Throne <hi>altogether guiltleſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I <hi>anſwer,</hi> That I doubt not but <hi>perſonal ſins,</hi> and acts of <hi>miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>government</hi> towards the people under their charge, are inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to <hi>Kings</hi> as well as to <hi>perſons</hi> of a <hi>lower degree.</hi> And I dare not perſwade my ſelf or others, that our <hi>late Sovereign</hi> was <hi>ſo much Saint,</hi> as to be <hi>altogether free;</hi> nay he was <hi>ſo much Saint,</hi> as (more then once) to <hi>confeſſe miſcarriages in his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">and why.)</note> But I muſt tell the enquirers withall, that I do not believe him one half ſo criminal, as popular prejudice, blown up by the breath of factious ſpirits endeavoured to make him. And for what was <hi>really amiſſe in him,</hi> I have this to plead, That <hi>Kings</hi> are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons under ſuch <hi>Tentations,</hi> as <hi>Vulgar capacities</hi> do not underſtand: that becauſe of their <hi>eminency</hi> and publique influence, the <hi>Tempter thruſts ſorer</hi> at them then ordinary, <hi>that they may fall;</hi> that <hi>God</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 118. 13.</note>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:43483:27"/> doth ſometimes <hi>lead them into Tentation,</hi> becauſe his <hi>wrath is kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt their people;</hi> that (in Scripture) thoſe who have the <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> 4. 1.</note> commendation of Gods Spirit for the <hi>beſt of Kings, (David</hi> and <hi>Solomon)</hi> have yet more and fouler ſpots upon their Names, than K. <hi>Charles;</hi> and that were the buſie enquirers into, and cenſurers of <hi>Kings faults</hi> a while in <hi>their places,</hi> I fear they would commit <hi>more</hi> and <hi>greater.</hi> Let the <hi>Questioniſt</hi> if he can, anſwer me <hi>this Queſtion, Si fueris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tu Leo, qualis eris?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a <hi>word,</hi> Were I ſufficiently inſtructed in the <hi>Cabinet affairs</hi> of our <hi>late Sovereign,</hi> and had I a <hi>revelation</hi> withall afforded me, to diſcover the <hi>ſecret ſprings</hi> of thoſe <hi>Counſels</hi> upon which he acted, and his own mind in acting; and were I inabled thereby to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude him really guilty of whatever, and more, then what malice and prejudice have ever charged him withall, I ſhould think my ſelf obliged to do (what is the duty of every <hi>good man)</hi> that <hi>right</hi> to his <hi>memory,</hi> as to <hi>bury his errours and miſcarriages</hi> in his grave, and <hi>proclaim his vertues</hi> as Royal examples to all Poſterity. The Lord diſcover to his <hi>Sacred Majesty,</hi> who now fils his <hi>Seat,</hi> (to whom this enquiry is more proper then to us) both <hi>theſe</hi> and <hi>thoſe,</hi> that he may render his <hi>vertues immortal</hi> by <hi>imitation,</hi> and waſh off the guilt of his <hi>failings,</hi> (if any ſuch adhere to the <hi>Throne)</hi> by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precating the imputation of them, and avoiding the incurſion of the like. And let us help him herein in our <hi>prayers,</hi> and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage him by our <hi>loyal affections</hi> and <hi>obedience;</hi> and <hi>amend our own lives</hi> the rather, upon the account of the <hi>Love</hi> we bear to <hi>his proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity;</hi> to whom our <hi>ſins</hi> (whatever they are) are <hi>Traitors,</hi> though our <hi>ſelves</hi> be never ſo <hi>loyal</hi> and <hi>affectionate ſubjects.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And for any ſort of <hi>partner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> in <hi>this</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular <hi>horrid fact,</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Let us grieve (and herein I am ſure <hi>David</hi> had not ſo much cauſe by <hi>Sauls</hi> own frequent confeſſion) for that <hi>special guilt</hi> which the <hi>Nation in general,</hi> and <hi>particular perſons</hi> in great multitudes eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where have contracted, by any way <hi>furthering antecedently,</hi> or <hi>abetting conſequentially,</hi> ſo horrid and execrable a murther.</p>
            <p>Let no <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Party</hi> think to ſhift off <hi>this duty,</hi> as that which only concerns ſuch and ſuch, who had the unhappineſſe to appear <note place="margin">(which few are clear of.)</note> in a <hi>contrary engagement</hi> to him <hi>in the field,</hi> (divers of whom, as hath appeared by many real evidences, have vindicated their inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity (with <hi>David)</hi> in this particular, notwithſtanding the foul reflections of ſome irreconcileable Zealots, (whoſe heat no <hi>Acts of Imdemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ity</hi> or <hi>Oblivion</hi> can ſlake) I ſay, let no man ſhift off this
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:43483:28"/> guilt upon <hi>others,</hi> becauſe he was engaged in a <hi>Party</hi> or <hi>Intereſt</hi> leſſe obnoxious to ſuch an imputation: For, by that time we all have ſeriouſly examined our ſelves upon theſe weighty <hi>Interrogato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> Whether we have not <hi>(antecedently</hi> to this ſad accident) had an hand in the heightning <hi>animoſities,</hi> and fomenting the <hi>differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> whether Religious or Civil, and ſowing <hi>prejudices</hi> and <hi>jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies,</hi> which gave occaſion to the <hi>publick conteſts?</hi> Nay, whether we <hi>did what we might,</hi> and to the utmoſt of our power, to keep them from <hi>arriving at ſuch an height?</hi> And whether <hi>(during</hi> the civil broyls) we (ſetting aſide the conſideration of the Quarrel, which (I hope) we ſhall all ſtrive to remember no more) have not been guilty of ſuch unjuſt <hi>oppreſſions,</hi> and <hi>exactions,</hi> and <hi>vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lences,</hi> as exaſperated <hi>oppoſite parties</hi> into an irreconcileableneſſe? Nay further, whether we <hi>interpoſed (at the time</hi> wherein that bloody Tragedy was acting) in all ſuch waies as were within the compaſſe of our capacity <hi>to hinder it? Some</hi> did indeed, but how <hi>few</hi> to the body of the Nation? Nay rather, whether we did not, by <hi>Petition,</hi> or other encouragement, <hi>promote</hi> it? Or if not, yet, whether we <hi>mourned</hi> for it, and <hi>deprecated</hi> the <hi>guilt</hi> of it? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther we <hi>declared (after</hi> the ſad blow given) our juſt <hi>abomination</hi> and <hi>deteſtation</hi> of the fact in our ſeveral places and capacities? <hi>Some</hi> indeed did (and let it be remembred to their everlaſting honour that they did ſo,) but how <hi>many</hi> were there (who ſhould have been more bold in ſuch a cauſe) in <hi>whoſe mouthes there were no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs?</hi> And laſtly, Whether <hi>(ex poſt facto)</hi> we have not <hi>juſtified</hi> the fact, by <hi>flattering Addreſses</hi> to the pretended Authority, of thoſe who <hi>uſurped</hi> the <hi>Royal Power</hi> ſucceſſively? Whether we have not <hi>laid our hands unjuſtly</hi> upon any of the <hi>Royal Revenues?</hi> Whether we have not <hi>contributed Money</hi> or <hi>Arms</hi> towards the <hi>oppoſition</hi> of his <hi>preſent Majeſties reſtitution?</hi> And (in a word) Whether we ſwallowed not the execrable <hi>Engagement</hi> againſt <hi>Kingſhip</hi> it ſelf, which very few (except only ſome <hi>nice Conſciences</hi> here and there, who valued their <hi>Allegiance</hi> at an higher rate) refuſed to ſubſcribe? I ſay, by that time every ones Conſcience hath ſeriouſly anſwered <hi>theſe Interrogatories,</hi> and many ſuch more as may be made, it will be well if <hi>Centeſimus quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> one of an hundred can before <hi>God</hi> and his own <hi>ſerious Conſcience,</hi> ſay, <hi>I am altogether innocent of this blood.</hi> O, that our <hi>Repentance</hi> might be as general as our <hi>Guilt;</hi> and that we might not by caſting it in <hi>each others</hi> Faces, think to clear <hi>our</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:43483:28"/> 
               <hi>ſelves</hi> from that which muſt be diſcharged and blotted out only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our <hi>particular</hi> and <hi>perſonal repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And Laſtly, Let us (as common <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> blinds us) <hi>grieve</hi> 
               <note place="margin">And (laſtly) for <hi>thoſe who are hardned</hi> in the <hi>guilt of this ſin.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>for thoſe</hi> who will not be perſwaded to <hi>grieve for themſelves,</hi> but are ſo <hi>obdurate</hi> in the error of their <hi>ſeduced Conſciences,</hi> that they ſecret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>applaud themſelves,</hi> and <hi>canonize others</hi> for <hi>Saints of an eminent Rank,</hi> upon the bare account of their influence upon, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement in this <hi>abominable Act.</hi> Alas I Poor ſeduced Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures! Can you imagine that God will own it as a piece of <hi>merit</hi> in you or any other, that you affront, and contemn, and injure (with the utmoſt indignity) his <hi>own deputed Authority?</hi> Would any of you, <hi>ſi parvis componere magna liceret,</hi> account your ſelves ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged by him who with the utmoſt ſtrength he can make, attempts the moleſtation or diſpoſſeſſion of a <hi>Tenant</hi> that holds in <hi>your right?</hi> Did you ever read in any Scriptural or Church-Records, that any Perſon was ever accounted a <hi>Martyr,</hi> that ſuffered for <hi>conſpiring,</hi> and much leſs, for <hi>murdering</hi> his Lawful <hi>Soveraign;</hi> excepting on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Black Kalendar of the Apoſtate Church of Rome?</hi> And ſhall thoſe who bid the greateſt defiance to <hi>Popery</hi> in their Profeſſion, forſake all the Churches of Chriſt in all Ages of the world, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>here to them, in a matter of ſuch concernment, and juſtifie <hi>Bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets</hi> and <hi>Garnets,</hi> and other ſuch <hi>Traytor-Saints,</hi> by vindicating them, in compariſon to whom, they were Saints indeed? O, let us pray for the Conviction of theſe deluded Souls, and if our Prayers prevail not, let us <hi>weep for them in ſecret,</hi> though they laugh never ſo much at our tenderneſs towards them, as a <hi>fooliſh pitty;</hi> and prophanely <hi>bleſs themſelves</hi> from our <hi>Charity,</hi> which their erroneous Conſciences judge <hi>miſtaken.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Wonder</hi> and <hi>Aſtoniſhment,</hi> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he monſtrous <hi>Confidence</hi> which <note place="margin">and in our <hi>wonder</hi> at the; amazing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence of the: <hi>late executed T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aytors.</hi>
               </note> animated thoſe Wretches who preſumed to <hi>ſit in Judgment,</hi> and <hi>paſs Sentence of Condemnation</hi> upon their <hi>Lawful Soveraign,</hi> and (after 12 years time vouchſafed them by God to repent in, before his Vengeance found them out) would fain perſwade <hi>God</hi> by their <hi>Prayers,</hi> and the <hi>World</hi> by their <hi>Speeches,</hi> that they dyed with <hi>Conſciences ſo innocent,</hi> in <hi>this matter,</hi> as to need <hi>no repentance.</hi> I profeſs ſolemnly, I was never more <hi>ſurprized with admiration,</hi> at any thing in my life, than I was upon the accidental view of that <hi>dangerous inſinuating piece</hi> (the poyſon whereof (I fear) hath i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted hundreds of ignorant and well-meaning people) <hi>The Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:43483:29"/> of the laſt Paſſages</hi> of the late <hi>deteſtable Traytors;</hi> and that, to ſee how <hi>Omnipotent a Deceiver</hi> (if I may ſo ſpeak) that <hi>Spirit of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror</hi> and <hi>Deluſion</hi> is, that can ſo artificially extract <hi>Heaven</hi> out of <hi>Hell,</hi> and not only <hi>Charm Conſcience</hi> (even upon the very Brink of Eternity) into a <hi>ſleep,</hi> but <hi>impoſe</hi> upon it with ſuch a <hi>Cheat</hi> as to abſolve and juſtifie in ſo high a manner thoſe <hi>Offenders,</hi> and ſo <hi>many of them</hi> (except we will ſuppoſe a Confederacy in ſuch an <hi>uniform reſolution,</hi> of purpoſe deſigned for the <hi>animating the relicks of a broken Party,</hi> which I can hardly be ſo uncharitable as to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve) whom both the <hi>Law of God,</hi> and the <hi>Dictates of Nature</hi> in the <hi>Principles of all Nations</hi> under Heaven condemn. For my part, I dare not <hi>judge</hi> their <hi>eternal eſtate:</hi> But this I muſt ſay (for the prevention of any evil <hi>Influence</hi> from their examples) that I would not for 10000 worlds run their <hi>hazard,</hi> for all their <hi>Confidences</hi> and Comforts. And if I had an <hi>Infallible Revelation,</hi> to tell me they were <hi>gone to Heaven,</hi> I ſhould think my ſelf bound, to <hi>keep it in my own Boſom,</hi> leſt the publiſhing of it ſhould occaſion the <hi>leading Millions to Hell;</hi> and pray God, to lead me to Heaven in a more <hi>ordinary</hi> and unſuſpected <hi>Rode,</hi> and keep me from being carried up to a <hi>Pinacle</hi> of <hi>spiritual Pride</hi> upon the <hi>Devils</hi> ſhoulders in the ſhape of an <hi>Angel of Light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Abomination</hi> of thoſe <hi>principles</hi> which tend to the like <hi>Practiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi> Of all <note place="margin">and <hi>abominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> of the <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ples</hi> that lead to ſuch <hi>horrid Crimes.</hi> Particularly the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s.</hi>
               </note> which (and theſe late years have been as fruitfull in <hi>Doctrines</hi> of this ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency, as <hi>Aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ica</hi> is of <hi>Monſters)</hi> there are none more deſperate, than thoſe of the <hi>Expectants of a Fifth Monarchy</hi> to be begun in the <hi>perſonal appearance of Chriſt upon earth to cruſh all Earthly Powers, and reign viſibly with his Saints a thouſand years before the ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eral Reſurrection,</hi> which fancy with abundance more ſtrange conceits of like nature, ſome <hi>confident new Doctors</hi> among them, pretend to gather from the <hi>Propheſies</hi> of <hi>Daniel,</hi> and the <hi>Apocalypſe</hi> ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly, that they have often preſumed to ſet and fix <hi>the time of his appearance.</hi> What a <hi>spirit</hi> theſe Princ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ples can <hi>conjure up,</hi> there needs no further evidence then the <hi>deſperate attempt</hi> made ſo lately, by an <hi>inconſiderable number</hi> of the <hi>men of that perſwaſion;</hi> whiles they are ſeduced to believe, that to make way for this <hi>Kingdom of Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>horrideſt murthers</hi> are <hi>meritorius,</hi> and the <hi>juſteſt executions</hi> for thoſe <hi>murthers, Martyrdom.</hi> But alas! poor men, would Chriſt come to ſet up a Temporal Kingdom, he hath waies enough of his own to effect it: So that
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Non tali Auxilio, nec Defenſoribus iſtis,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Christus eget.—</hi>
                  </l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Christ</hi> hath no more need of <hi>their Arms</hi> to further it, then <hi>we</hi> have of <hi>their Principles,</hi> from <hi>both</hi> which, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi> AMEN.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:43483:29"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
